<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ochlo-machia. Or The peoples war, examined according to the principles of Scripture &amp; reason, in two of the most plausible pretences of it. In answer to a letter sent by a person of quality, who desired satisfaction. By Jasper Mayne, D.D. one of the students of Ch. Ch. Oxon.</title>
            <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 21 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89005</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1472</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E398_19</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R201695</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862194</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862194</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160373</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89005)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160373)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 63:E398[19])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Ochlo-machia. Or The peoples war, examined according to the principles of Scripture &amp; reason, in two of the most plausible pretences of it. In answer to a letter sent by a person of quality, who desired satisfaction. By Jasper Mayne, D.D. one of the students of Ch. Ch. Oxon.</title>
                  <author>Mayne, Jasper, 1604-1672.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By L. Lichfield],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeare, 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first word of the title is printed in Greek characters.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July 15".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Divine right of kings --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Government, Resistance to --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160373:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ΟΧΛΟ-ΜΑΧΙΑ. OR <hi>THE PEOPLES WAR,</hi> EXAMINED According to the Principles of SCRIPTURE &amp; REASON, IN Two of the moſt Plauſible Pretences of it.</p>
            <p>IN ANSWER To a LETTER ſent by a Perſon of Quality, who deſired ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>By JASPER MAYNE D.D. one of the Students of Ch. Ch. <hi>Oxon.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Rom. 13.2.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Yeare, 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:160373:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:160373:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Honourd Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Have in my time ſeen certain <hi>Pictures</hi> with two <hi>faces.</hi> Beheld one way, they have preſented the <hi>ſhape</hi> and <hi>fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure</hi> of a <hi>Man.</hi> Beheld another, they have preſented the <hi>ſhape</hi> and <hi>figure</hi> of a <hi>Serpent.</hi> Me thinks, Sir, for ſome years, whatever <hi>Letters</hi> the <hi>King</hi> wrote either to the <hi>Queene,</hi> or his <hi>friends,</hi> or what ever <hi>Declarations</hi> he publiſh in the defence of his <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Cauſe,</hi> had the ill for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to undergoe the fate of ſuch a <hi>Picture.</hi> To us who read them impartially, by their own true, genuine <hi>light,</hi> they ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared ſo many cleare, tranſparent <hi>Copies</hi> of a ſincere and Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant <hi>Mind.</hi> Look't upon by the People, (of whom you know who ſaid <hi>populus iſte <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> decipi, decipiatur</hi>) through the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers</hi> and <hi>Obſervations,</hi> and venomous <hi>Comments,</hi> which ſome men made upon them, a <hi>fallacy</hi> in <hi>judgement</hi> followed very like the <hi>fallacy</hi> of the <hi>ſight;</hi> where an <hi>Object</hi> beheld through a falſe deceitfull <hi>medium,</hi> partakes of the <hi>coſenage</hi> of the <hi>convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi> and <hi>way,</hi> and puts on a falſe <hi>Reſemblance.</hi> As <hi>ſquara, bright, angular</hi> things through a miſt ſhow <hi>darke</hi> and <hi>round;</hi> and <hi>ſtraight</hi> things ſeen through water ſhow <hi>broken</hi> and <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It ſeems, Sir, by your <hi>Letter</hi> to me, that your <hi>Friend, with whom you ſay, you have lately had a dispute about the Kings Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy, and the Subjects Rights,</hi> is one of thoſe who hath had the ill luck to be thus <hi>depeived.</hi> Which I doe not wonder at, when I conſider how much he is concern'd in his fortunes that the <hi>Parliament</hi> ſhould all this while be in the <hi>right.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:160373:3"/>Sir, Having lookt upon the Cauſe of that <hi>Side</hi> meerly in that <hi>plauſible dreſſe</hi> with which ſome <hi>pens</hi> have attired it, And having entertain'd a ſtrong <hi>prejudice</hi> againſt whatever ſhall be ſaid to prove that a <hi>Parliament</hi> may <hi>erre,</hi> it ought to be no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaile to you, if he be rather of M. <hi>Prinnes</hi> then Iudge <hi>Jenkins's</hi> Opinion; And perſwade himſelfe, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> having, if not a <hi>ſuperior,</hi> yet a <hi>coordinate power</hi> with the <hi>King,</hi> in which the <hi>People</hi> is intereſſed, where ever their <hi>Religion</hi> or <hi>Liberty</hi> is invaded, may take up Armes againſt Him, for the defence of <hi>either.</hi> But then, Sir, finding by my reading of the <hi>publick writings of both ſides,</hi> that <hi>both ſides</hi> challenged to themſelves the <hi>Defence</hi> of one and the ſame <hi>Cauſe,</hi> I muſt confeſſe to you, That for a while the many <hi>Battailes,</hi> which ſo often <hi>coloured</hi> our fields with <hi>Bloud,</hi> appeared to me like <hi>Battails</hi> fought in <hi>Dreams.</hi> Where the <hi>perſon</hi> combaring in his ſleepe, imagines he hath an <hi>Adverſary,</hi> but awake perceives his <hi>error</hi> that he held conflict with <hi>himſelfe.</hi> To ſpeak a little more freely to you, Sir, the <hi>Kings Declarations,</hi> and the <hi>Parliaments Remonſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> equally pretending to the maintenance of the ſame <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Religion,</hi> and the ſame <hi>Liberty</hi> of the Subject. I wonde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red a while how they could make two <hi>oppoſite ſides,</hi> or could ſo frequently come into the field without a <hi>Quarrell.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſince your <hi>Friend</hi> is pleaſed to let me no longer remain a <hi>Sceptick,</hi> but clearly to ſtate the <hi>Quarrell;</hi> by ſuffering the two great words of <hi>Charme, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> (from whence <hi>both ſides</hi> have ſo often made their <hi>Recruits</hi>) to ſtand no longer as a <hi>Salamis,</hi> or <hi>controverted Hand</hi> between two e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall <hi>Challengers;</hi> And ſince he is pleaſed to eſpouſe the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of <hi>them</hi> ſo wholly to the <hi>Parliament,</hi> as to call the <hi>Warre</hi> made by the <hi>King</hi> the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of them; Both for <hi>his</hi> and <hi>your</hi> ſatisfaction, who have layed this taske upon me, give me leave to propoſe this reaſonable <hi>Dilemma</hi> to you. Either 'tis <hi>true</hi> what your <hi>Friend</hi> ſaies, that the <hi>Parliament</hi> hath all this while fought for the defence of their <hi>Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Religion,</hi> or 'tis on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a <hi>pretence,</hi> and hath hid ſome <hi>darker ſecret</hi> under it. If it have been only a <hi>pretence,</hi> there being not a third word in all the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:160373:3"/>World which can afford ſo good <hi>Colour</hi> to make an <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Warre</hi> paſſe for a <hi>juſt,</hi> the firſt <hi>diſcovery</hi> of it, will be the <hi>fall,</hi> and <hi>ruine</hi> of it; And the <hi>People</hi> who have been miſled with ſo much <hi>holy Impoſture,</hi> will not only hate it for the <hi>Hypocriſie,</hi> but the <hi>Injuſtice</hi> too. If it be <hi>true,</hi> yet I cannot ſee how they are hereby advantaged, or how, <hi>ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> or <hi>both</hi> theſe joyned can <hi>legitimate</hi> their <hi>Armes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For <hi>firſt,</hi> Sir, I would fain know of your <hi>friend,</hi> what he means by the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Subject.</hi> I preſume he doth not mean a <hi>Releaſement from ſervitude.</hi> Since amongſt all their other <hi>complaints,</hi> delivered in <hi>Petitions</hi> to the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> they never yet adventured to ſay that they were go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd as <hi>Servants</hi> by a hard <hi>Maſter,</hi> not as <hi>Subjects</hi> by a <hi>Prince.</hi> Nor doe I find that the <hi>King</hi> was ſuch a <hi>Pharaoh</hi> to them, that they were able to ſay, that he changed a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome</hi> of <hi>Freemen</hi> into a <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Bondage.</hi> Some <hi>Acts</hi> of his <hi>Government,</hi> I confeſſe, ſome have call'd <hi>Illegal;</hi> namely the exaction of <hi>Ship-mony.</hi> But this certainly, was a <hi>grievance</hi> which if it had not been <hi>redreſt,</hi> deſerved not to be reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed among the <hi>Brick kills</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> or to denominate his <hi>Government despoticall</hi> too.</p>
            <p>Next then, doth your <hi>friend,</hi> by <hi>Liberty,</hi> meane a <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſement</hi> from <hi>Tyranny,</hi> as <hi>Tyranny</hi> allowes men to be <hi>Subjects,</hi> but not much removed from <hi>ſlaves?</hi> Had the <hi>King</hi> indeed, made his <hi>Will</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of his <hi>Government,</hi> and had his <hi>Will</hi> revealed it ſelfe in nineteen years of <hi>Injuſtice,</hi> had he like <hi>Caligula,</hi> worne a <hi>Table-book</hi> in his pocket, with the names of the <hi>Nobility</hi> in it <hi>deſign'd</hi> and <hi>Marks</hi> for ſlaughter; Had he without any Trialls of Law made his <hi>pleaſure</hi> paſſe for <hi>ſentence,</hi> and lopt off <hi>Senators heads</hi> as <hi>Tarquin</hi> did <hi>Poppeys;</hi> Had he in his oppreſſions of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made them feele <hi>Times</hi> like thoſe which <hi>Tacitus</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes; where no man durſt be <hi>virtuous,</hi> leaſt he ſhould be thought to upbrayd his <hi>Prince;</hi> where to complaine of hard uſage was <hi>capitall;</hi> and where men had not only their <hi>words,</hi> but their very <hi>looks</hi> and <hi>ſighs</hi> proſcribed; his Raigne would
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:160373:4"/>beare that <hi>Name.</hi> But alas, Sir, you your ſelfe know, that theſe are <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Tyranny,</hi> which were ſo ſarre from being <hi>practiſed,</hi> that they have not yet been <hi>faigned</hi> among us. 'Tis true, indeed, certain <hi>dark Jealouſies</hi> were caſt among the people, as if ſome <hi>Evill Counſellors</hi> about the King had had it in their deſigne to introduce an <hi>Arbitrary Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</hi> But theſe were but <hi>Jealouſies,</hi> blown by thoſe, whoſe plot 'twas to make the <hi>popular hatred</hi> their engine to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move thoſe <hi>Counſellors,</hi> that by their <hi>ruine</hi> they might raiſe a <hi>Ladder</hi> to their own <hi>Ambitions.</hi> For if the Calamity of <hi>theſe times</hi> have not quite blotted out the memory of <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> people cannot but remember, that no <hi>Nation</hi> under Heaven, more freely enjoyed the Bleſſing of the <hi>Scripture</hi> then <hi>we; every one ſecure under the ſhade of his own <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine,</hi> perhaps a grape or two <hi>extraordinary</hi> was gathered for the <hi>publique.</hi> But if any did refuſe to contribute, I doe not find that like <hi>Naboth,</hi> they were ſtoned for their <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ineyard.</hi> If therefore, the Gentleman your <hi>friend</hi> underſtand <hi>Liberty</hi> in this ſenſe, the moſt he can ſay for the <hi>Parliament,</hi> is, that they have taken up Armes againſt their <hi>King,</hi> not becauſe he <hi>was,</hi> but becauſe he poſſibly <hi>might</hi> be a <hi>Tyrant.</hi> Which <hi>feare</hi> of theirs being in it ſelfe altogether <hi>unreaſonable,</hi> and therefore not to be ſatisfied, could not but naturally endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (as we find by ſad experience it hath done) to ſecure it ſelfe by removing out right the <hi>formidable Object</hi> which cauſed it. which being not to be done but by the Removall of <hi>Monarchicall Government</hi> it ſelfe, could not but caſt them at length upon a <hi>new forme</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> or ſuch a <hi>confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> or <hi>no Forme</hi> of <hi>state,</hi> as, we ſee, hath almoſt drawn ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine upon <hi>themſelves</hi> and their <hi>Countrey.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Once more therefore, I muſt aske your <hi>Friend</hi> what he meanes by <hi>Liberty.</hi> I hope he doth not mean an <hi>Exempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> from all <hi>Government;</hi> Nor is fallen upon their <hi>wilde O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,</hi> who held that there ought to be no <hi>Magistrate,</hi> or <hi>superior</hi> among <hi>Christians.</hi> But that in a <hi>freedom</hi> of <hi>condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> we are to live together like men ſtanding in a <hi>Ring,</hi> or
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160373:4"/>
               <hi>Circle,</hi> where <hi>Roundneſſe</hi> takes away <hi>Diſtinction,</hi> and <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der;</hi> And where every one beginning and ending the <hi>Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle,</hi> as none is <hi>before,</hi> ſo none is <hi>after</hi> another. This Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as 'twould quickly reduce the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Lords</hi> to the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons;</hi> ſo 'twould in time reduce the <hi>Houſe</hi> of <hi>Commons</hi> to the ſame levell with the <hi>Common people,</hi> who being once taught that <hi>Inequality</hi> is <hi>unlawfull,</hi> would quickly be made <hi>Docile</hi> in the entertainment of the other <hi>Arguments,</hi> upon which the <hi>Anabaptists</hi> did heretofore ſet all <hi>Germany</hi> in a flame. Namely, that Chriſt hath not only bequeathed to Men, the <hi>liberty</hi> of his <hi>Gospell,</hi> but that this <hi>liberty</hi> conſiſts in one not being greater then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. It being an <hi>Oracle</hi> in <hi>Nature,</hi> that we are all borne <hi>Equall;</hi> That theſe words of <hi>Higher,</hi> and <hi>Lower, Superiour,</hi> and <hi>Inferiour,</hi> are fitter for <hi>Hills,</hi> and <hi>Vales,</hi> then for <hi>men</hi> of a <hi>Kind;</hi> That the names alſo of <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Subject, Magiſtrate</hi> and <hi>People, Governours</hi> and <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> are but ſo many ſtiles <hi>Vſurpe.</hi> Since in Nature for one Man to be borne <hi>Subiect</hi> to another, is as much againſt Kinde, as if men ſhould come into the World with <hi>chaines</hi> about them; or as if Women ſhould bring forth Children with <hi>Gyves,</hi> and <hi>ſhakles</hi> on. Which Doctrine as 'twould naturally tend to a <hi>Parity,</hi> ſo that <hi>Parity</hi> would as naturally end in a <hi>Confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, therefore, I will underſtand your <hi>Friend</hi> in the moſt favourable ſence I can. That by the <hi>Parliaments de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence</hi> of the <hi>Peoples Liberty,</hi> he meanes the maintenance of ſome <hi>Eminent Rights</hi> belonging to the <hi>Subiect,</hi> which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in manifeſt danger to be <hi>invaded,</hi> and taken from them, could not poſſibly be preſerved but by Armes taken up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>invader.</hi> But then, granting this to be true, (as I ſhall in fit place ſhew it to be falſe) yet the <hi>King</hi> being this <hi>invader</hi> (unleſſe by ſuch an <hi>Jnvaſion</hi> He could ceaſe to be their <hi>King,</hi> or they to be his <hi>subiects.</hi>) I cannot ſee how ſuch <hi>Rights</hi> could make their <hi>Defence lawfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the clearer <hi>Demonſtration</hi> of this, I ſhall deſire you;
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160373:5"/>Sir, not to think it a digreſſion in me, if I deduce things ſome what higher then I at firſt intended, or then <hi>your Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> requires me; Or, if to cure the <hi>ſtreame,</hi> I take the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> courſe, and caſt <hi>ſalt</hi> into the <hi>spring;</hi> And examine firſt, How farre the <hi>Power</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> (who is <hi>truly</hi> a King, and not one only in <hi>Name</hi>) extends it ſelfe over <hi>Subjects.</hi> Next, whether any ſuch Power doe belong to <hi>our King;</hi> Thirdly if there doe, How farre 'tis to be <hi>obeyed,</hi> and not <hi>reſiſted.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the firſt, you ſhall in the <hi>Scripture,</hi> Sir, find two <hi>Originalls</hi> of <hi>Kings, One</hi> immediatly ſpringing from the <hi>Election</hi> and <hi>choice</hi> of <hi>God himſelfe.</hi> The <hi>other</hi> from the <hi>choice</hi> and <hi>election</hi> of the <hi>People;</hi> But ſo, as that it reſolves it ſelfe into a <hi>Divine Institution.</hi> The Hiſtory of <hi>Regall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> as it took Originall from <hi>God himſelfe,</hi> is ſet downe at large in the eight Chapter of the firſt Book of <hi>Samuel,</hi> where, when the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> weary of the Government by <hi>Judges</hi> (who had the ſame power that the <hi>Dictators</hi> had at <hi>Rome,</hi> and differ'd nothing from the moſt <hi>abſolute Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs</hi> but only in their <hi>Name,</hi> and the <hi>temporary uſe</hi> of their <hi>power</hi>) required of <hi>Samuel</hi> to ſet a <hi>King</hi> over them, <hi>God</hi> bid him <hi>hearken to their voyce.</hi> But withall<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 9.</note> 
               <hi>Solemnly to proteſt</hi> and <hi>ſhew them the manner</hi> (or as one tranſlates it more to the <hi>mind</hi> of the <hi>Originall, J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Regis,</hi> the <hi>Right,</hi> or <hi>power</hi>) of the <hi>King</hi> that ſhould raigne over them. That <hi>he would take their ſonnes, &amp; appoint them for his Charets;</hi> And <hi>their Daughters, to be Confectionaries, and Cookes for his Kitchin.</hi> That he would alſo take their <hi>fields, their <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine-yards, and their Olive-yards, even the beſt of them and give them to his Officers;</hi> Laſtly, That he would take the <hi>Tenth of their ſeed, and ſheepe,</hi> And <hi>yee,</hi> ſaies the <hi>Prophet</hi> (which is a very characteriſticall marke of <hi>subjection</hi>)<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 17.</note> 
               <hi>ſhall be his servants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All which <hi>particulars,</hi> with many others there ſpecifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, (which I forbeare to repeat to you, becauſe they riſe but to the ſame height) may in other termes be briefly ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med up into theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Generalls.</hi> That the <hi>Jews</hi> by requir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160373:5"/>a King to be ſet over them, (ſuch a <hi>King</hi> as was to Raigne over them, like the <hi>Kings of other</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>V.</hi> 5.</note> 
               <hi>Nations</hi>) diveſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves of two of the greateſt <hi>Immunities</hi> which can belong to <hi>Freemen, Liberty</hi> of <hi>perſon,</hi> and <hi>propriety</hi> of <hi>Eſtates.</hi> And both theſe in ſuch an <hi>unlimited meaſure,</hi> as left them not power, if their <hi>Prince</hi> pleaſed, to call either <hi>themſelves,</hi> or <hi>Children,</hi> or <hi>any thing</hi> elſe their <hi>owne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this if either you, or your <hi>friend</hi> ſhall reply, that this was but a <hi>Propheticall Character</hi> of <hi>Saul,</hi> and a meere <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction</hi> to the people what <hi>He</hi> made King would doe, noe true <hi>Draught</hi> of his <hi>Commiſſion,</hi> what He in <hi>Iuſtice</hi> might, (ſince a <hi>Prince</hi> who ſhall aſſume to Himſelfe the exerciſe of ſuch a <hi>boundleſſe power,</hi> doth but verify the <hi>Fable,</hi> a <hi>Stork</hi> ſet over a Commonwealth of <hi>Froggs,</hi> They to be his <hi>prey,</hi> not He to be their <hi>King</hi>) To the firſt I anſwer <hi>negatively.</hi> That what is ſaid in the fore-mentioned Chapter by <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel,</hi> cannot be meant only of <hi>Saul,</hi> ſince nothing is there ſaid to confine the deſcription to this <hi>Raigne.</hi> Nor doth any part of his Hiſtory charge him with ſuch a <hi>Government.</hi> Next, I ſhall grant you, that no <hi>Prince</hi> ruling by the ſtrict Lawes of <hi>naturall-equity,</hi> or <hi>Justice,</hi> can exerciſe all the <hi>Acts</hi> of power there mentioned. Nor can his being a <hi>King</hi> ſo legitimate all his <hi>Actions,</hi> or ſo outright exempt him from the common condition of men, that what ever he ſhall doe ſhall be right. Moſt of the <hi>Acts</hi> there recorded are not only repugnant to the Lawes of <hi>ſocrable Nature,</hi> or <hi>juſt Rule</hi> (which forbids <hi>One</hi> to have <hi>All;</hi> and binds <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi> themſelves in chains of <hi>Reaſon</hi>) but to the<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Deuter.</hi> 17. <hi>v.</hi> 16, 17, 18, 19.</note> Law of <hi>God</hi> in another place; which allowes not the <hi>King</hi> of his own chovce, to Raigne as he liſt, but aſſignes him the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> for his <hi>Rule.</hi> From which as often as he broke looſe, he ſinned like one of the People. yet ſo, as that upon any ſuch breach of the <hi>Law</hi> 'twas not left in the power of the People to <hi>correct</hi> him, or to <hi>force</hi> him by a <hi>Warre,</hi> like <hi>ours,</hi> to returne back again to his <hi>duly.</hi> His commiſſion towards them (if you marke it well) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in ſuch an uncontroleable ſtile,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:160373:6"/>that his <hi>beſt Actions</hi> and his <hi>worſt,</hi> towards them, wore the ſame warrant of <hi>Authority.</hi> However therefore, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall power,</hi> in the forementioned place of <hi>Samuel,</hi> be called the <hi>manner</hi> of what a King would doe, yet that <hi>Manner,</hi> (as I told you before) carryed a <hi>Jus</hi> or <hi>power</hi> with it <hi>unque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionable</hi> by the <hi>Subject,</hi> to doe if he pleaſed <hi>things unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</hi> And hence 'tis that the <hi>Prophet</hi> tells the <hi>Iews</hi> at the 18. verſe of that Chapter; That in <hi>the Day they found them. ſelves oppreſt by their King, they ſhould cry out for redreſſe to the Lord;</hi> As the only <hi>Arbiter,</hi> and <hi>Iudge,</hi> of the <hi>Deeds,</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> of <hi>Princes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Originall of <hi>Regall power</hi> as it took beginning from the People, you have moſt lively expreſt to you by S. <hi>Peter</hi> in the 13. v. of the 2. Chapter of his 1. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> Where ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horting thoſe to whom he wrote to order their <hi>Obedience</hi> according to the ſeverall <hi>Orbes,</hi> and <hi>Regions</hi> of <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>States</hi> wherein they lived, he bids them <hi>ſubmit themſelves to every Ordinance of Man; whether it be to the King as ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme, or unto Governors, as unto them who are ſent by him &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which words I ſhall deſire you to obſerve. Firſt, that <hi>Monarchy</hi> as well as other <hi>Formes</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> is there called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Human Creature,</hi> or thing of Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Creation. From whence <hi>ſome,</hi> ſuch as your <hi>Friend,</hi> (who, I perceive by his <hi>Arguments</hi> againſt <hi>Monarchy</hi> in your <hi>Letter</hi> hath read <hi>Iunius Brutus,</hi> and <hi>Buchanan</hi>) have inferred, That as to avoid <hi>Diſorder</hi> and <hi>Confuſion,</hi> people did at firſt paſte over the <hi>Rule</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> of themſelves to a <hi>Prince,</hi> ſo the <hi>Prince</hi> being but an <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or <hi>Derivative</hi> from them, doth ſtill retain a <hi>Dependance</hi> on his firſt <hi>Creators.</hi> And as in Nature 'tis obſerved that waters naturally cannot riſe higher then their <hi>Spring-head;</hi> ſo Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, they ſay, have their <hi>Spring head</hi> too. Above which as often as they exalt themſelves, 'tis in the power of the <hi>Fountain</hi> to recall it's <hi>ſtreame,</hi> and to bring it to a <hi>plaine,</hi> and <hi>level</hi> with it ſelfe. For though, ſay they, it be to be granted,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:160373:6"/>that a <hi>King</hi> thus choſen is <hi>Major ſingulis, ſuperiour</hi> to any <hi>One,</hi> yet he is <hi>Minor vneverſis, Inferior</hi> to the <hi>whole.</hi> Since all the <hi>Dignity</hi> and <hi>power</hi> which makes him ſhine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>People,</hi> being but their <hi>Rayes</hi> contracted into his <hi>Body,</hi> they cannot reaſonably be preſumed ſo to give them away from themſelves, as that in no caſe it ſhall be lawfull to call for them back againe.</p>
            <p>For anſwer to which <hi>Opinion</hi> (taken in by your <hi>Friend</hi> from his miſunderſtanding of that Text) I will goe no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the place of <hi>Scripture</hi> on which 'tis built, where (without any <hi>criticall</hi> ſtrife about the ſignification of the Words) I will grant that not only <hi>Monarchy,</hi> (which is the <hi>Government</hi> of a <hi>People</hi> by a <hi>Prince</hi>) But <hi>Ariſtocracy,</hi> (which is the <hi>Government</hi> of a <hi>People</hi> by <hi>States</hi>) &amp; <hi>Demo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cracy</hi> (which is the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>people</hi> by the <hi>people</hi>) hath next, and immediatly in all States but the <hi>Iewiſh</hi> been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>Humane Creation.</hi> But then that 'tis not ſo purely <hi>humane,</hi> as not to be of <hi>Gods Creation,</hi> and <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution</hi> too, is evident by the words next in Contexture, where the Apoſtle bids them, to whom he wrote, to <hi>ſubmit themſelves to every ſuch Ordinance of man,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>For the Lords ſake,</hi> who by putting his <hi>Se<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> of Approbati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on foment <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>chay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> hath not only authoriſed a <hi>Humane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> paſſe into a <hi>Divine Ordinance;</hi> But towards it hath imprinted even in <hi>Nature</hi> it ſelfe ſuch a <hi>Neceſſity</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> and of <hi>Superiority</hi> of one man over another, that men without any other Teacher, but their owne inbredde <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> which have alwayes whiſper'd to them that <hi>Anarchy</hi> is the Mother of <hi>Confuſion</hi>) have naturally fallen into <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> and <hi>Commonwealths.</hi> And however ſuch a ſtate, or condition of life under a <hi>Prince</hi> or <hi>Magiſtate</hi> be ſome thing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>free</hi> then not to be ſubject at all, (ſince mens Actions have hereby <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Wills</hi> of <hi>Superiours,</hi> whoſe <hi>Lawes</hi> have been certaine <hi>chained</hi> and <hi>ſhackles</hi> clapt upon them,) yet a <hi>ſubjection</hi> with <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> hath alwayes, by wiſe men, been preferr'd before <hi>Liberty</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:160373:7"/>with <hi>danger,</hi> &amp; men have bin compelled to enter into thoſe <hi>Ronds,</hi> as the only way, &amp; meanes to avoyd a greater <hi>Thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> Since without ſuch a <hi>ſubordination</hi> of one man to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to hold them together in juſt <hi>ſociety,</hi> the Times of the <hi>Nomades</hi> would return, where, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the <hi>weaker</hi> ſerved only to be made a prey to the <hi>ſtronger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next thing which I ſhall deſire you to obſerve from that <hi>Text,</hi> is, that the <hi>Kings</hi> though choſen, and created by the People, is there ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Supreame.</hi> Now Sir, you know that to be <hi>Supream,</hi> is ſo to be over others, as to have no <hi>Superiour</hi> above him. That is, to be ſo <hi>Jude<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendently</hi> the Lord of his owne <hi>Actions,</hi> of what ſort ſoever, whether <hi>uniuſt</hi> or <hi>juſt,</hi> as not to be accountable to any but <hi>God.</hi> If he were, that <hi>other,</hi> to whom he is <hi>accounta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> would be <hi>Supream,</hi> not He. Since in all things where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is <hi>Queſtionable.</hi> He is no longer the <hi>King,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> there deſcribed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> but a more <hi>spacious Subject.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon will either follow this <hi>contradiction</hi> in <hi>Power,</hi> That the ſame Perſon at the ſame Time may be a <hi>King,</hi> and no <hi>King;</hi> or we muſt admit of an <hi>Abſurdity</hi> as great; which is, That a <hi>Supream</hi> may have a <hi>Supream;</hi> which to grant were to caſt our ſelves upon an <hi>Infinite progreſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For that there muſt be a <hi>Non-ultra,</hi> or <hi>Reſolution</hi> of pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er either into one, (as in a perfect <hi>Monareby</hi>) or into <hi>ſome Few,</hi> (as in the <hi>Government</hi> by a <hi>Senate</hi>) or into the <hi>Maior part</hi> of the People joyning ſuffrages, (as in a pure <hi>Democracy;</hi> All three Formes agreeing in this, That ſome body muſt be <hi>Supream</hi> and <hi>unqueſtionable</hi> in their <hi>Actions,</hi>) the nature of <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>Buſineſſe,</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> it ſelfe demonſtrates to us. Which would not else be able to obtaine it's <hi>ends,</hi> or decide <hi>controverſies</hi> otherwiſe <hi>undeter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable.</hi> And however this power may ſometimes be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed, and ſtrained beyond it's <hi>Juſt limits,</hi> yet this not being the fault of the <hi>power,</hi> but of the <hi>Perſons</hi> whoſe power 'tis, it makes much more for the Peace of the <hi>publique,</hi> that <hi>one,</hi> or <hi>Few,</hi> ſhould in ſome things be allowed to be <hi>unjust,</hi> then that they ſhould be liable to be <hi>Queſtioned</hi> by an <hi>Ill. Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Multitude</hi> in <hi>All.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:160373:7"/>
The third thing which you may pleaſe to obſerve from that peece of <hi>Scripture,</hi> is, The <hi>Creation</hi> of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> or <hi>Governours,</hi> who are there ſaid to be <hi>ſent</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>By Him.</hi> Where a <hi>Moderne Writer</hi> applyes the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>By Him,</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> As if all other <hi>Governours</hi> were <hi>ſent by Him,</hi> not by the <hi>King.</hi> Which Interpretation of the place I would admit for currant, if by the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Governours,</hi> ſo <hi>ſent,</hi> he did underſtand the <hi>Rulers</hi> in an <hi>Ariſtocracie,</hi> or <hi>Free-ſtate,</hi> which being a <hi>Species</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> Contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct to <hi>Monarchy,</hi> cannot be denyed to have God, as well as the other for it a <hi>Founder.</hi> But then the word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the peculiar <hi>Epithet</hi> of <hi>Monarchy,</hi> will beare another ſence then I have hitherto given it; And will not only ſignifie the <hi>King</hi> to be <hi>Supream,</hi> (for ſo the <hi>Rulers</hi> of a <hi>Free State</hi> are within their owne <hi>Territories</hi>) but compared with other <hi>Formes</hi> of <hi>Supremacy</hi> to be the moſt excellent. <hi>Monarchy</hi> being in it ſelfe leaſt ſubject to <hi>Diſunion,</hi> or civill <hi>Diſturb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</hi> And for that Reaſon pronounced by the wiſeſt <hi>State<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſts</hi> to be that <hi>Forme</hi> of <hi>Government,</hi> into which all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther incline naturally to reſolve themſelves for their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. But by <hi>Governours,</hi> in that place, underſtanding as he doth, not the <hi>Senate</hi> in a <hi>Free-ſtate,</hi> but the <hi>Subordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Magiſtrates,</hi> under a <hi>Prince,</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly belongs to the <hi>King.</hi> To whom the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> there aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes the <hi>Miſſion</hi> of <hi>Governours</hi> as one of the <hi>Eſſentiall Markes,</hi> and <hi>Notes,</hi> that He is, in His owne <hi>Realm Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus Sir, having drawne the portraiture of <hi>Regall Power</hi> to you, by the beſt <hi>Light</hi> in the world, but with the meaneſt <hi>Pencill;</hi> I know you expect that in the next place I ſhould ſhew you what <hi>Rayes,</hi> or <hi>Beames,</hi> of this <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> are <hi>Jnherent</hi> in <hi>our King.</hi> Which being a taske fitter for one of our <hi>greateſt Sages</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> then for <hi>me,</hi> (who, being One who doe not pretend to any exact knowledg in the <hi>Fundamentall Lawes,</hi> or <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> of this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> which are to ſtand the <hi>Land-marks</hi> and markes of <hi>partition</hi> between the <hi>Kings Prerogative,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject,</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:160373:8"/>may perhaps be thought by drawing a <hi>line</hi> or <hi>eircle</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout <hi>either,</hi> to limne <hi>Figures</hi> in the <hi>Duſt,</hi> whoſe fate hangs on the <hi>Mercy</hi> of the next <hi>Winde</hi> that blowes) the ſteps by which I will proceed, (leaving you to the late writings of that moſt <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>honeſt Judge Ienkins</hi> for your fuller ſatisfaction in this point) ſhall be breifly theſe two. Firſt I will ſhew you what are the <hi>Genuine markes,</hi> and <hi>proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of Supream power;</hi> Next, how many of them have been <hi>challenged</hi> by the <hi>King,</hi> and have not hitherto been <hi>denyed</hi> Him by any <hi>Publique Declaration</hi> of the <hi>Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sir if you have read <hi>Ariſtotles Politicks</hi> (as I preſume you have) you may pleaſe to remember that he * there di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vides the <hi>Supream Powere</hi> of a <hi>State,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> into three <hi>generall parts.</hi> The <hi>Ordering</hi> of Things for the <hi>publique,</hi> the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> and the <hi>Finall</hi> reſolution of <hi>Judgment</hi> upon <hi>Appeales;</hi> To which he afterwards addes the power of <hi>Levying Warre,</hi> or <hi>concluding</hi> of <hi>Peace,</hi> of making or breaking <hi>Leagues</hi> with forraigne <hi>Nations,</hi> of enacting or abrogating <hi>Lawes,</hi> of Pardoning, or Puniſhing <hi>Offenders,</hi> with Baniſhment, Confiſcation, Impriſonment or Death. To which <hi>Dyoniſius Halicarnaſſenſis</hi> addes, the power to call or diſſolve <hi>Comitia,</hi> or <hi>publique Aſſemblies;</hi> As well <hi>Synods</hi> and <hi>Councells</hi> in Deliberations concerning <hi>Religion;</hi> as <hi>Parliaments,</hi> or <hi>Senates,</hi> in Deliberations <hi>ſecular</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the <hi>State.</hi> To all which markes of <hi>Supreame power,</hi> a * <hi>Moderne Lawyer</hi> (who only wants their <hi>Age</hi> to be of as great <hi>Authority</hi> as <hi>either</hi>) addes the power to <hi>exact Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gret. lib. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi> de Jure Belli &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis.</note> and to <hi>preſſe Souldiers.</hi> It the exerciſe of which <hi>two Acts</hi> conſiſts that <hi>Dominium Eminens,</hi> or <hi>Dominion Rara mount,</hi> which the <hi>State,</hi> (when ever it ſtands in need, And <hi>that</hi> too, to be the <hi>Judge</hi> of its owne <hi>Neceſſity</hi>) hath not only over the <hi>Fortunes,</hi> but the <hi>Perſons</hi> of the <hi>Subject;</hi> In a meaſure ſo much <hi>greater</hi> then <hi>they</hi> have over <hi>themſelves,</hi> as the <hi>publique poole</hi> is to be preferr'd before the <hi>private Ciſterne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now Sir, if you pleaſe to apply this to the <hi>King,</hi> though <hi>good Lawyers</hi> will tell you that the power of making or
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:160373:8"/>repealing <hi>Laws</hi> be not <hi>ſolely</hi> in <hi>Him,</hi> but that the <hi>two Houſes</hi> have a <hi>concurrent right</hi> in their <hi>production,</hi> and <hi>Aboliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment:</hi> yet they will tell you too, that His power extends thus farre, that no <hi>Law</hi> can be <hi>made</hi> or <hi>repealed</hi> without Him. Since for <hi>either,</hi> or <hi>both Houſes</hi> to produce a <hi>Stat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ute Law</hi> by <hi>themſelves,</hi> hath alwaies, in this State, been thought a <hi>Birth</hi> as <hi>Monſtrous</hi> as if a <hi>Child</hi> ſhould be <hi>begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten</hi> by a <hi>Mother</hi> upon <hi>her ſelfe. They</hi> uſually are the <hi>Matrice</hi> and <hi>Womb,</hi> where <hi>Lawes</hi> receive their firſt <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnation,</hi> and are <hi>ſhap't</hi> and <hi>formed</hi> for the <hi>publique;</hi> But (beſides the opinion of all preſent <hi>Lawyers</hi> of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, who, like that great<note n="*" place="margin">Judg Ien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins.</note> 
               <hi>example</hi> of <hi>Loyalty,</hi> dare ſpeak their knowledge) it hath alwaies been acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the <hi>Law</hi> made 2. <hi>H.</hi> 5. By the <hi>ſentence</hi> of <hi>Refuſall, Le Roy S' Aviſera</hi> and indeed by all Parliaments of <hi>former Ages,</hi> That the <hi>King</hi> is thus farre <hi>Pater Patria:</hi> that theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> are but <hi>abortive</hi> unleſſe his <hi>Conſent</hi> paſſe upon them. A <hi>Negative power</hi> He hath then, though not an out right <hi>Legiſlative.</hi> And if it be here objected, by your <hi>Friend,</hi> that the <hi>two Houſes</hi> ſeverally have ſo too, I ſhall perhaps grant it, if in this particular, they will be <hi>modeſt,</hi> and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to go ſharers in this <hi>Power,</hi> And no longer challenge to their <hi>Ordinances</hi> the legality &amp; force of <hi>Acts of Parliament.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the other parts of <hi>Royalty,</hi> which I reckoned up to you; As the <hi>Creation</hi> of <hi>Officers,</hi> and <hi>Counſellours</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> of <hi>Iudges</hi> for <hi>Law,</hi> and Commanders for Warre, the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering of the <hi>Militia</hi> by Sea and Land, The <hi>Benefit</hi> of <hi>Confiſcations,</hi> and <hi>Eſcheats</hi> where Families want an <hi>Heyre;</hi> The power to <hi>abſolve</hi> and <hi>pardon,</hi> where the <hi>Law</hi> hath <hi>Condemned;</hi> The power to <hi>call</hi> and <hi>diſolve Parliaments,</hi> As alſo the Receipt of Cuſtome and Tribute, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other particulars, which you are able to ſuggeſt to your ſelfe. They have alwaies been held to be ſuch undoubted <hi>Flowers</hi> of this <hi>Crowne,</hi> that every one of them like his <hi>Coyne</hi> (which you know Sir, is by the <hi>Law</hi> of this Land <hi>Treaſon</hi> to <hi>counterfeit,</hi> which is an other mark of <hi>Royalty</hi>) hath in all <hi>Ages</hi> but <hi>Ours,</hi> worne the Kings <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage,</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:160373:9"/>and ſuperſcription upon it. Not to be invaded by any, without the crime of <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And though (as your <hi>Friend</hi> ſaies,) this be but a <hi>regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated power,</hi> and riſe no higher in the <hi>juſt exerciſe</hi> of theſe <hi>Acts,</hi> then a <hi>Truſt</hi> committed by the <hi>Lawes</hi> of this <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> for the Governement of it, to the <hi>King,</hi> (for I never yet perceived by any of His <hi>Declarations,</hi> That His Majeſty claimed theſe as due to Him by <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Conqueſt,</hi> or any other of thoſe <hi>Abſolute,</hi> and <hi>Vnlimited</hi> waies, which might tender His Crowne <hi>Patrimoniall</hi> to Him, or ſuch an out-right <hi>Allodium</hi> that He mi ht <hi>Alienate</hi> it, or chuſe His <hi>Succeſſour,</hi> or Rule as He pleaſed Himſelfe) yet as in the <hi>making</hi> of theſe <hi>Lawes</hi> He holds the <hi>firſt place,</hi> ſo none of theſe <hi>Rights</hi> which he derives from them, can without His own <hi>Conſent,</hi> be taken from Him.</p>
            <p>For proofe hereof, I will only inſtance in three particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars to you, (for I muſt remember that I am now writing a <hi>Letter</hi> to you, not penning a <hi>Treatiſe,</hi>) which will carry the greater force of perſwaſion, becauſe confeſt by this <hi>Parliament.</hi> The firſt was an <hi>Act</hi> preſented to the <hi>King</hi> for the ſetling of the <hi>Militia,</hi> for a limited time in ſuch Hands as they might <hi>confide</hi> in. A clear Argument, that without ſuch an <hi>Act</hi> paſt by the <hi>King,</hi> the <hi>two Houſes</hi> had nothing to do with the <hi>Ordering</hi> of it. Another was one of the <hi>Nineteen Propofitions,</hi> where twas deſired that the <hi>Nomination</hi> of all <hi>Officers,</hi> and <hi>Counſellours</hi> of <hi>State,</hi> might, for the future go by the <hi>Maior part</hi> of <hi>Voyces</hi> of <hi>both Houſes.</hi> Another Argument, That the <hi>King</hi> hath hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto in all ſuch <hi>Nominations,</hi> been the only <hi>Fountaine</hi> of <hi>Honour.</hi> The third was, the paſſing of the <hi>Act</hi> for the <hi>Continuation</hi> of this <hi>Parliament;</hi> Another Argument, that nothing but the <hi>Kings conſent</hi> could ever have made it thus <hi>Perpetuall</hi> as it is. Many other <hi>Instances</hi> might be giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, but foundoubtedly acknowledged by <hi>Bracton,</hi> By <hi>Him</hi> that wrote the <hi>Book</hi> call'd <hi>The Prerogative of Parliaments,</hi> (who is thought to be Sir <hi>Walter Raleigh</hi>) By Sir <hi>Edward
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:160373:9"/>Cooke,</hi> by the <hi>ſtiles</hi> and <hi>Formes</hi> of all the <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which have been made in this Kingdom, and by that learned<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Sir</hi> Iohn Banks.</note> Iudge who wrote the <hi>Examination of ſuch parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars in the Solemne League and Covenant as concerne the Law;</hi> And who in a continued <hi>Line</hi> of <hi>Quotation,</hi> and <hi>Proofe,</hi> derives along <hi>theſe</hi> and the <hi>other</hi> parts of <hi>Supreme power</hi> in the <hi>King,</hi> from <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Confeſſour,</hi> to our preſent <hi>Soveraigne King Charles,</hi> that to prove them to you, were to adde <hi>beames</hi> to the <hi>Sunne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here then, For the better ſtating of the <hi>Third thing</hi> I pro oſed to you, (which was, That granting the <hi>King</hi> to be <hi>Supreme</hi> in this Kingdome, (at leaſt ſo farre as I have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed him) how farre He is to be <hi>Obeyed,</hi> and not <hi>reſist<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi>) Two things will fall under <hi>Inquiry.</hi> Firſt, ſuppoſing the <hi>King</hi> not to have kept Himſelfe to that <hi>Circle</hi> of <hi>power</hi> which the Lawes have drawn about Him, but deſirous to walke in a more <hi>Abſolute compaſſe,</hi> That He hath in ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>things invaded the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>People,</hi> whither ſuch an <hi>Jncroachment</hi> can juſtifie their <hi>Armes.</hi> Next, If it be proved that He hath kept within his <hi>Life,</hi> and only made the <hi>Law</hi> the <hi>Rule</hi> of His <hi>Governement,</hi> whether a bare <hi>Fear</hi> or <hi>Iealouſie,</hi> That when ever he ſhould be able, He would change this <hi>Rule,</hi> (which is the moſt that can be pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed) could be a <hi>Juſt cauſe</hi> for an <hi>Anticipating Warre.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Deciſion of the firſt of theſe <hi>Inquiries</hi> will depend wholly upon the <hi>Tenure</hi> by which he holds His <hi>Crowne.</hi> If it were puerly <hi>Elective,</hi> or were at firſt ſet upon His <hi>Head</hi> by the <hi>Suffrages</hi> of the <hi>people;</hi> And if in that <hi>Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> His power had been <hi>limited;</hi> Or if by way of <hi>paction,</hi> it had been ſaid, Thus farre the <hi>King</hi> ſhall be <hi>Supreme,</hi> thus farre the <hi>people</hi> ſhall be <hi>Free;</hi> If there had been certaine <hi>Expreſſe conditions</hi> aſſigned Him, with his <hi>Scepter,</hi> that if he tranſgreſt not his <hi>limites</hi> He ſhould be <hi>Obeyed,</hi> if He did, it ſhould be lawfull for the <hi>people</hi> to <hi>reſiſt</hi> Him; Laſtly, if to hinder ſuch <hi>Exorbitances,</hi> there had been certaine <hi>Epho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri,</hi> or <hi>Inspectours,</hi> or a <hi>Co-ordinate Senate,</hi> placed, as
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:160373:10"/>
               <hi>Mounds,</hi> and <hi>Cliffes</hi> about Him, with warrant from the <hi>Electours,</hi> that when ever he ſhould attempt to <hi>overflow</hi> his <hi>Bankes,</hi> it ſhould be their part to <hi>reinforce</hi> Him back into his <hi>Channell;</hi> I muſt confeſſe to you being no better then a <hi>Duke</hi> of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>enice,</hi> or a <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Sparta;</hi> In truth no King, but a more <hi>splendid Subject,</hi> I think ſuch a <hi>Reſiſtance</hi> might be Lawfull. Since, ſuch a Conveyance of <hi>Empire</hi> being but a <hi>conditionall contract,</hi> as in all other <hi>Elections,</hi> the <hi>chuſers</hi> may reſerve to themſelves, or give away ſo much of their <hi>Liberty</hi> as they pleaſe. And where the part reſerved is <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaded,</hi> 'Tis no <hi>Rebellion</hi> to defend. But where the <hi>Crowne</hi> is not <hi>Elective,</hi> but hath ſo <hi>Hereditarily</hi> deſcended in an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>line</hi> of <hi>succeſſion</hi> from <hi>King</hi> to <hi>King,</hi> that to finde out the <hi>Originall</hi> of it, would be a taske as difficult, as to find out the <hi>Head</hi> of <hi>Nilus;</hi> where the <hi>Tenure</hi> is not <hi>conditionall,</hi> nor hangs upon any <hi>contract</hi> made at firſt with the <hi>people,</hi> nor is ſuch a <hi>reciprocall Creature</hi> of their <hi>Breath,</hi> as to be blowne from them, and recalled, like the fleeting Ayre they draw, as often as they ſhall ſay it returnes to them, worſe then as firſt they ſent it forth; In ſhort, Sir, Where the only <hi>Obligation,</hi> or <hi>Tye</hi> upon the <hi>Prince</hi> is the <hi>Oath</hi> which He takes at his <hi>Ceronation,</hi> to rule according to the <hi>knowne Lawes</hi> of the place; Though every <hi>Breach</hi> of ſuch an <hi>Oath</hi> be an Offence againſt God, (to whom alone a Prince thus <hi>independent</hi> is <hi>accountable</hi> for his <hi>Actions</hi>) yet 'twill never paſſe for more then <hi>perjury</hi> in the <hi>Prince;</hi> No War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for <hi>Subiects</hi> to take up <hi>Armes</hi> againſt Him.</p>
            <p>Here then, Sir, ſhould I ſuppoſe the worſt that can be ſuppoſed, that there was a time when the <hi>King,</hi> miſled (as your <hi>Friend</hi> ſayes) by <hi>Evill Counſellours,</hi> did actually trample upon the <hi>Lawes</hi> of the <hi>Kingdome,</hi> and the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>Subiects,</hi> derived to them by thoſe Lawes; yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſome <hi>Originall compact</hi> can be produced where 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, That upon every ſuch <hi>Incroachment</hi> it ſhall be lawfull for them to ſtand upon their <hi>Defence;</hi> unleſſe ſome <hi>Funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall Contract</hi> can be ſhewen where 'tis clearely ſaid,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:160373:10"/>that where the King ceaſeth to <hi>governe</hi> according to <hi>Law,</hi> He ſhall for ſuch <hi>miſgovernment</hi> ceaſe to be <hi>King;</hi> To urge (as your <hi>Friend</hi> doth) ſuch <hi>vnfortunate precedents</hi> as a <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed Richard,</hi> or a <hi>Dethroned Edward,</hi> (Two diſpropor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd examples of <hi>popular Fury;</hi> The one forced to part with his <hi>Crowne</hi> by <hi>Reſignation,</hi> the other as never having had <hi>legall Title</hi> to it,) may ſhew the <hi>Iniuſtice</hi> of <hi>former Parliaments</hi> growne <hi>ſtrong,</hi> never juſtifie the <hi>Pitcht-feilds</hi> which have been fought by <hi>this.</hi> Since, (If this ſuppoſition were true) the <hi>King</hi> being bound to make the <hi>Law</hi> His <hi>Rule</hi> by no other <hi>Obligation</hi> but His <hi>Oath</hi> at His <hi>Corona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> (Then which there cannot be a greater, I confeſſe, and where 'tis <hi>violated</hi> never, without <hi>Repentance</hi> ſcapes vnpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh't) yet 'tis a <hi>trespaſſe</hi> of which <hi>Subiects</hi> can only com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine, but as long as they are <hi>Subiects</hi> can never innocent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>revenge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But this, all this while, Sir, is but only <hi>ſuppoſition;</hi> And you now, Sir, what the <hi>Logician</hi> ſaies, <hi>ſuppoſitie nihil p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nit in eſſe,</hi> what ever may be <hi>ſuppoſed</hi> is not preſently <hi>true.</hi> If <hi>Calumny</hi> her ſelfe would turne <hi>Informer,</hi> let her leave out <hi>Ship-money</hi> (a <hi>greivance</hi> which being fairely laid a fleepe by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> deſerved not to be awakened to beare a part in the <hi>preſent Tragedy</hi> of this almoſt <hi>ruined Kingdome</hi>) ſhe muſt confeſſe that the <hi>King</hi> through the whole courſe of His <hi>Raigne</hi> was ſo farre from the <hi>Invaſion</hi> of His Subjects <hi>Rights,</hi> that no <hi>King</hi> of <hi>England</hi> before Him, (unleſſe it were <hi>Henry</hi> the <hi>firſt,</hi> and <hi>King Iohn,</hi> whom, being <hi>Vſurpers</hi> it concern'd to comply with the <hi>People,</hi> the <hi>one</hi> having <hi>ſupplanted</hi> his Eldeſt Brother <hi>Robers Duke</hi> of <hi>Normandy,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> his <hi>Nephew, Arthur Prince</hi> of <hi>Britaine</hi>) ever imparted to them ſo many <hi>Rights</hi> of his <hi>owne.</hi> To that Degree of <hi>Infranchiſment</hi> that I may almoſt ſay He exchanged <hi>Liberties</hi> with them. Witneſſe the <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> of <hi>Right.</hi> An <hi>Act</hi> of ſuch <hi>Royall Grace,</hi> that when He paſt that <hi>Bill,</hi> He almoſt dealt with His <hi>people,</hi> as <hi>Traian</hi> did with the <hi>Pratorian praefect,</hi> put his <hi>ſword</hi> into their <hi>Hands,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:160373:11"/>and bid them uſe it for Him if he ruled well, if not, againſt Him. In ſhort, Sir, <hi>Magna Charta</hi> was a <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ine,</hi> I confeſſe, caſt over the <hi>People,</hi> but this <hi>Act</hi> enabled them to call the <hi>ſhade</hi> of it their <hi>owne,</hi> An <hi>Act</hi> which (if your <hi>friend</hi> will pleaſe to forget <hi>Ship mony</hi>) being in no one particular vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, ſo farre as to be inſtanced in by <hi>thoſe,</hi> whoſe preſent Ingagements would never ſuffer ſuch <hi>Breaches</hi> of <hi>Priviledge</hi> to paſſe <hi>unclamour'd,</hi> will oblige poſterity to be gratefull, as often as they remember themſelves to be <hi>Freemen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then being ſo, the next <hi>inquiry</hi> will be, whether a bare <hi>Jealouſy</hi> that the <hi>King</hi> would in time have <hi>recalled</hi> this <hi>Grace,</hi> and would have invaded the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his <hi>Subjects,</hi> by the change of the <hi>Fundamentall Lawes,</hi> could be a <hi>just cauſe</hi> for ſuch a <hi>preventive Warre</hi> as this. To which I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, that ſuch a <hi>Faire,</hi> though built upon <hi>ſtrong preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions</hi> cannot poſſibly be a <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> for one <hi>Nation</hi> to make Warre upon another; much leſſe for Subjects to make Warre againſt their Prince. The Reaſon is, becauſe nothing can <hi>legitimate</hi> ſuch a <hi>Warre,</hi> but either an <hi>Injury</hi> already <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered,</hi> or ſo viſibly <hi>imminent,</hi> that it may paſſe for the firſt <hi>Dart</hi> or <hi>Speare</hi> hurled. Where the <hi>Injury</hi> or <hi>Invaſion,</hi> is only contingent and conjecturall, and wrapt up in the <hi>wombe</hi> of <hi>darke Counſells,</hi> no way diſcoverable but by their own <hi>revelation</hi> of themſelves in ſome outward <hi>Acts</hi> of <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtility,</hi> or <hi>uſurpation,</hi> to <hi>anticipate</hi> is to be firſt <hi>injurious;</hi> and every Act of <hi>prevention,</hi> which hath only <hi>Iealouſie</hi> for its foundation, will adde new juſtice to the enemies <hi>Cauſe.</hi> who, as He cannot in reaſon be pronounced guilty of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Feares</hi> ſo he will come into the Field with this great advantage on his <hi>ſide,</hi> That his <hi>reall wrong</hi> will joyne Battle with the others <hi>weake ſuspition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But alas, Sir, <hi>Time,</hi> (the beſt <hi>interpreter</hi> of Mens <hi>Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi>) hath at length unſee'ld our eyes, and taught us that <hi>this</hi> hath been a Warre of a quite <hi>oppoſite Nature.</hi> The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman who wrote the <hi>Defence of M. Chaloners Speech,</hi> and <hi>M. Chaloner</hi> himſelfe, if you marke his <hi>Speech</hi> well, will
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:160373:11"/>tell you, that the <hi>quarrell</hi> hath not been whether the <hi>subject</hi> of <hi>England</hi> ſhall be <hi>Free,</hi> but whether this <hi>Freedome</hi> ſhall not conſiſt in being no longer Subject to the King. If you marke, Sir, How the <hi>face</hi> of things hath <hi>alter'd</hi> with <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe,</hi> How the <hi>ſcene</hi> of things is <hi>ſhifted;</hi> And in what a <hi>New ſtile</hi> they, who called themſelves the <hi>Invaded,</hi> have ſpoken, ever ſince their <hi>Victories</hi> have ſecured them againſt the <hi>power</hi> of <hi>any</hi> that ſhall <hi>invade;</hi> If you conſider what a poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick uſe hath been made of thoſe words of Inchantment, <hi>Law, Liberty,</hi> and <hi>Propriety</hi> of the Subject, by which the People have been <hi>muſically</hi> enticed into their <hi>Thraldome;</hi> If you yet farther conſider the more then <hi>Decemvirall pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> which this Parliament hath aſſumed to it ſelfe, by <hi>repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing old Lawes,</hi> and making <hi>Ordinances</hi> paſſe for <hi>new;</hi> If you yet farther will pleaſe to conſider How much <hi>Heavyer</hi> that which ſome call <hi>Priviledge</hi> of <hi>Parliament,</hi> hath been to the Subject, then that which they ſo much complained of. The <hi>Kings Prerogative,</hi> ſo much <hi>heavyer,</hi> that if <hi>one</hi> deſerved to be called a <hi>Little finger,</hi> the <hi>other</hi> hath ſwolne it ſelfe into a <hi>Loyne,</hi> Laſtly, if you compare <hi>Ship, mony</hi> with the <hi>Exciſe,</hi> and the many other <hi>Taxes</hi> laid upon the Kingdome, you will not onely find that a <hi>whippe then,</hi> hath been heightned into a <hi>Scorpion now;</hi> but you will perceive, that as <hi>theſe</hi> are not the firſt <hi>Subjects</hi> who, under pretence of <hi>Liberty,</hi> have invaded their <hi>Princes Crowne,</hi> (ſo farre as the <hi>Cleaving</hi> of Him <hi>aſunder</hi> by a <hi>State Diſtinction,</hi> which ſeparates the Power of the <hi>King</hi> from his Perſon) ſo <hi>ours,</hi> as long as he was able to lead an <hi>Army</hi> into the <hi>Field,</hi> hath been the <hi>first King</hi> that ever took up <hi>Armes</hi> for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. Vpon all which <hi>premiſes,</hi> Sir, I hope you will not think it falſe <hi>Logicke</hi> if I build this <hi>Concluſion</hi> ſo agreeable to the Lawes of the Kingdome, as well as the Lawes of God; That ſupooſing the Parliament all this while to have fought, (as was at firſt pretended) for the <hi>Defence</hi> of their <hi>aſſayled Liberty;</hi> yet fighting againſt the <hi>King</hi> whoſe Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects they are, it can never before a <hi>Chriſtian Judge,</hi> make
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:160373:12"/>their <hi>Armies</hi> paſſe for juſt. But being no way <hi>neceſſitated</hi> to make ſuch a <hi>Defence</hi> (their <hi>Liberty</hi> having in no one particular been aſſaulted, which hath not been <hi>redrest</hi>) if S. <hi>Paul</hi> were now on earth againe, and were the <hi>Iudge</hi> of this <hi>Controverſy</hi> between them and their Lawfull Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne, I feare he would call their <hi>Defence</hi> by a <hi>Name,</hi> which <hi>we</hi> in our <hi>Moderne Caſes</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> doe call <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, Sir, having as compendiouſly as the <hi>Lawes</hi> of a <hi>Letter</hi> will permit, given you, I hope, ſome <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> concerning the <hi>firſt part</hi> of your <hi>zealous Friends diſpute</hi> with you; which was, whether the <hi>Two Houſes</hi> (which he calls the <hi>Parliament</hi>) have not a <hi>Legall power,</hi> in <hi>Defence</hi> of their <hi>Liberty,</hi> to take up Armes againſt the <hi>King,</hi> I will with the like brevity, proceed as well as I can, to give you <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> in the <hi>ſecond part</hi> of his <hi>Diſpute</hi> alſo; which was, whether <hi>Religion</hi> may not be a <hi>juſt Cauſe</hi> for a Warre. The Termes of which <hi>Queſtion</hi> being very <hi>generall,</hi> and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained to any <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> or any <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>Warre,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>offenſive</hi> or <hi>defenſive,</hi> or whether of one <hi>Nation</hi> againſt <hi>another,</hi> or of a <hi>Prince</hi> againſt his <hi>Subjects,</hi> or of the <hi>Subjects</hi> back again againſt their <hi>Prince,</hi> allow me a very large ſpace to walk in. In which, leaſt I be thought to <hi>wander,</hi> and not to <hi>prove,</hi> It will firſt be neceſſary, that I <hi>define</hi> to you what <hi>Religion</hi> in generall is; And next, that I examine, whether every <hi>Religion</hi> which falls within the Truth of that <hi>Defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> may for the propagation of it ſelfe be a juſt cauſe of a Warre; and ſo whether all they who either are of <hi>no Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> or a <hi>falſe,</hi> may not be <hi>forced</hi> to be of the <hi>true.</hi> Laſtly, what the <hi>Duty</hi> of <hi>Subjects</hi> is towards their <hi>Prince,</hi> in caſe he ſhould endeavour by force to impoſe a <hi>Religion</hi> upon them which they think to be <hi>falſe;</hi> and can probably make it appear to be ſo by proofes taken from the <hi>Scripture;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Religion</hi> then, (to <hi>define</hi> it in the neareſt Termes) is ſaies <note n="*" place="margin">1. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. q. 60.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.3.</note> 
               <hi>Aquinas, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irtus reddens debitum Honorem Deo, A vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue which renders to God his juſt Honour.</hi> This payment of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:160373:12"/>
               <hi>Honour</hi> to <hi>God</hi> as 'tis built and founded upon his <hi>Creation</hi> of us, by which he hath a <hi>Right</hi> to our <hi>Service</hi> and <hi>Worſhip</hi> of him, ſo in the <hi>contemplative</hi> part of it, it conſiſts in theſe foure <hi>Notions</hi> or <hi>Apprehenſions</hi> of him. Firſt, that there is a <hi>God,</hi> and that there is but <hi>One.</hi> Next, that he is not any part of this <hi>Viſible World,</hi> but ſomething <hi>Higher</hi> and more <hi>excellent,</hi> then any Thing we ſee. Thirdly, that he hath a <hi>providence</hi> going in the World, and takes care of <hi>Humane affaires.</hi> Laſtly, that he <hi>made</hi> and <hi>created</hi> the World. To every one of which foure, anſwers a <hi>Commandement</hi> in the <hi>Firſt. Table</hi> of the <hi>Decalogue.</hi> Where the <hi>firſt</hi> deſcribes His <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity,</hi> by forbidding the Worſhip of <hi>other</hi> Gods. The <hi>next</hi> his <hi>Inviſibility,</hi> by forbidding any <hi>Image,</hi> or <hi>Reſemblance</hi> to be made of Him. The <hi>third</hi> his <hi>providonce,</hi> deſcribed there by two eminent parts of it. His <hi>Omniſcience,</hi> by which he knowes the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of mens <hi>Hearts;</hi> and his <hi>Juſtice,</hi> by which he inflicts puniſhments on thoſe whoſe <hi>Thoughts</hi> are diſproportion'd to their <hi>Oathes</hi> and <hi>Words.</hi> The <hi>Fourth</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares his <hi>Omnipotence,</hi> by which he created the World, and appointed the <hi>Sabbath</hi> to be the <hi>Feaſt</hi> and <hi>Memoriall</hi> of that great Worke. From which <hi>speculative apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of him doe ſpring theſe <hi>practicall,</hi> That being ſuch a <hi>God thus known,</hi> He is to be <hi>Honour'd, Lov'd, Fear'd, Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipt,</hi> and <hi>Obey'd.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now ſince mens <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>Worſhip</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> cannot in reaſon be required to reach higher then their <hi>Knowledge</hi> of Him, (for <hi>Manifeſtation</hi> is ſo neceſſary to <hi>Obligation</hi> and <hi>Duty,</hi> that if 'twere impoſſible to know that there is a God, 'twould be no ſinne to be an <hi>Atheiſt</hi>) ſo if God had never made any <hi>ſecond Revelation</hi> of Himſelfe by the <hi>Scripture,</hi> but had left <hi>Mankind</hi> to their own <hi>Naturall ſeareh</hi> of Him, and to thoſe <hi>Diſcourſes</hi> of their <hi>Mindes,</hi> by which they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred that ſuch an orderly <hi>frame</hi> and <hi>systeme</hi> of thinge, where every one works to the <hi>good</hi> and <hi>End</hi> of another, is too <hi>rationally</hi> contrived to ariſe from a concourſe of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomes,</hi> or to be the Creature of <hi>Chance,</hi> and therefore muſt
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:160373:13"/>have ſome <hi>Efficient Cauſe</hi> higher, and nobler then it ſelfe, (ſince it implies a <hi>Contradiction,</hi> that any thing ſhould be it's own <hi>producer</hi>) yet his bare <hi>Creation</hi> of the <hi>World</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſents ſo much of him, that without any other <hi>Booke</hi> or <hi>Teacher,</hi> all Ages have believed that there is a <hi>God</hi> who made the <hi>World;</hi> and that He hath a <hi>Rule,</hi> and <hi>providence</hi> going in it.</p>
            <p>This then being ſo, 'Tis the <hi>Opinion</hi> of a very<note n="*" place="margin">Grot. l. <hi>2.</hi> de Jure Bel li ac pacis c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Learned Moderne Writer,</hi> That if there ſhould be found a <hi>Countrey</hi> of <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> or a <hi>People</hi> of <hi>Diagoras Melius s</hi> Opinion, or of the opinion of <hi>Theodorus</hi> the <hi>Cyrenian,</hi> whoſe Doctrine 'twas, <hi>Nullos eſſe Dees, inane coelum,</hi> That there is no <hi>God</hi> nor a <hi>habitable Heaven,</hi> But that ſuch <hi>Names of Emptineſſe</hi> have been the <hi>Creatures</hi> of <hi>ſuperſtitious fancies,</hi> whoſe <hi>fears</hi> firſt prompted them to <hi>make Gods,</hi> and then to <hi>worſhip</hi> them; or if there ſhould be a <hi>People</hi> found of <hi>Epicurus</hi> his opinion, who held that there were <hi>Gods,</hi> but that they were <hi>Idle, careleſſe, vacant Gods,</hi> who troubled not themſelves with the <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>World,</hi> but paſt their time away in an <hi>undiſturbed Tranquillity</hi> and <hi>exemption</hi> from ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferior <hi>buſineſſes</hi> as the <hi>Actions</hi> of <hi>Men</hi> ſuch opinions (ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing them to be <hi>Nationall</hi>) as they are contradictory not only to the Dictates of <hi>Naturall Reaſon,</hi>) upon which <hi>God</hi> hath built the forementioned <hi>precepts</hi> of the <hi>Decalogue</hi>) but to that univerſally received <hi>Tradition,</hi> That there is a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine power;</hi> whoſe <hi>providence</hi> holds the ſcales to mens <hi>acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> and firſt or laſt ſides with <hi>afflicted Innocence</hi> againſt <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cesfull Oppreſſion,</hi> ſo they would be <hi>juſt Cauſes</hi> for <hi>a reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Warre,</hi> Not only becauſe they are contumelious &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proachfull to <hi>God</hi> himſelfe, but becauſe being directly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive to all <hi>Religion,</hi> They are by neceſſary conſequence deſtructive to <hi>Humane ſociety</hi> too. For let it once be gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that there is no <hi>God,</hi> or (which, with reference to <hi>States,</hi> and <hi>Common-wealths,</hi> will produce the ſame <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular effects</hi>) that he regards not mens <hi>Actions,</hi> nor trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles himſelfe with the Diſpenſation of <hi>Rewards</hi> and <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:160373:13"/>and the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Carneades</hi> will preſently paſſe for reaſonable; That <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tility</hi> is the <hi>meaſure</hi> of <hi>Right;</hi> And that he is moſt in the <hi>wrong</hi> who is leaſt able to defend himſelfe. That <hi>Juſtice</hi> in the <hi>virtue</hi> of <hi>Fooles;</hi> and ſerves only to betray the <hi>ſimple</hi> and <hi>phlegmaticke,</hi> to the more <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive</hi> and <hi>daring.</hi> In ſhort, Take away <hi>providence,</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the two great parts of it, which raigne in the Hearts of men, <hi>hope</hi> of <hi>Reward,</hi> and <hi>feare</hi> of <hi>Puniſhment,</hi> and mens <hi>worſt</hi> Actions, and their <hi>beſt</hi> will preſently be thought <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quall.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Lawes,</hi> the Bonds of <hi>Humane Society,</hi> wanting their juſt Principle, which upholds them in their <hi>Reverence,</hi> will inevitably looſe their force, and fall aſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; and Men will be Men to each other in nothing but their mutuall <hi>injuſtice</hi> &amp; <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> of one another. 'Twas there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the politick obſervation of an <hi>Atheiſt</hi> in<note n="*" place="margin">Adv. Mathemat. p. <hi>3.8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sextus Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piricus,</hi> That, to keep men orderly, and regular in a <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth,</hi> wiſe men at firſt invented <hi>Lawes,</hi> But per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that theſe, reaching only to their <hi>outward Actions,</hi> would never be well kept, unleſſe they could find a way to a we their Minds within too, as a meanes conducing to that end, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one more <hi>wiſe,</hi> and <hi>ſubtle</hi> then the reſt, invented <hi>Gods</hi> too. Well knowing that Religion, though but fained, is a <hi>conſervative</hi> of <hi>States.</hi> upon conſideration of which <hi>harmefull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences,</hi> which naturally follow <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and the deniall of Gods <hi>providence,</hi> 'tis the opinion of that <hi>Author,</hi> that as 'twas no <hi>Injustice</hi> in thoſe <hi>Grecian Citties,</hi> which baniſht <hi>Philoſophers,</hi> who were of this <hi>Opinion,</hi> out of their <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monwealth,</hi> ſo if there ſhould be found a <hi>Nation</hi> of ſuch <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plous perſwaſions,</hi> 'twould be no <hi>Injuſtice</hi> in any other <hi>People,</hi> who are not <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> by way of puniſhment, to ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh them out of the <hi>World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Though this, Sir, were the opinion of <hi>one,</hi> whoſe works have deſervedly made him ſo Famous to the whole <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on World</hi> (beſides the peaceableneſſe of his <hi>Writings</hi> which decline all the wayes of <hi>quarrell</hi>) that to <hi>erre</hi> with him
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:160373:14"/>would be no diſreputation to me, yet I muſt confeſſe to you, that I am ſo farre from thinking any Warre made for the <hi>propagation</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> how true ſoever it be, is warrant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, that in this particular, I perſwade my ſelfe I have ſome reaſon to diſſent from Him; and to think it a <hi>Probleme</hi> very diſputable, if his ſuppoſition were true, that there were ſuch a <hi>Countrey</hi> of <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> or <hi>Epicureans,</hi> who ſhould deny that there is a <hi>God,</hi> or that he hath a <hi>providence</hi> going in the <hi>World;</hi> whether for that reaſon only another <hi>Nation</hi> might juſtifiably make Warre upon them. For firſt, what ſhould give them Authority to doe ſo? Is't becauſe men of this deſperate perſwaſion doe ſinne very grievouſly againſt God? Granting this to be true, to the utmoſt aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of their offence, that this <hi>speculative error</hi> in their Mindes, drawes a <hi>practicall errour</hi> after it in their <hi>lives,</hi> which is, not to pay <hi>Worſhip</hi> to a <hi>God,</hi> which either they think not <hi>to be,</hi> or not at all to <hi>regard</hi> them, yet this being but a crime againſt God, the ſame Author hath anſwered himſelfe in another <hi>Paragraph,</hi> where he ſaies, <hi>Deorum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uria Dèis curae.</hi> That <hi>God</hi> is able to revenge the injuries committed againſt <hi>Himſelfe.</hi> Next then, is't becauſe ſuch an <hi>Opinion</hi> is deſtructive of <hi>Humane Society?</hi> Truly, Sir, though I ſhall grant that ſaying of <hi>Plutarch</hi> to be true, that <hi>Religion</hi> (which <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and the denyall of <hi>providence</hi> doe deſtroy) is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one, (nay one of the firmeſt) <hi>Bonds</hi> of <hi>Society,</hi> and <hi>ſupperters</hi> of <hi>Lawes,</hi> yet I have not met with any <hi>demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative</hi> Argument, which hath proved to me, that there is ſuch a neceſſary dependance of <hi>Humane ſociety</hi> upon <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> that the Abſence of the <hi>One</hi> muſt inevitably be the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the <hi>other.</hi> If it be, this is moſt likely to come to paſſe in the <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Commonwealth,</hi> which is of this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion among themſelves; Not in a forraigne <hi>State,</hi> or <hi>Common-wealth</hi> which is not. But ſince 'tis poſſible that a Countrey of <hi>Atheiſts</hi> may yet have ſo much <hi>Morality</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them, ſeconded by <hi>Lawes</hi> made by common agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:160373:14"/>among themſelves, as to be a <hi>People,</hi> and to hold the ſociety of <hi>Citizens</hi> among themſelves. And as 'tis poſſible for them, without <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo farre, for meere <hi>utility</hi> and <hi>ſafeties</hi> ſake, to obſerve the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nations,</hi> as not to wrong or injure a <hi>People</hi> different from themſelves, ſo where no <hi>civill wrong,</hi> or <hi>enjury</hi> is offered by them to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>People,</hi> but where the <hi>morall Bonds</hi> of <hi>Society,</hi> and <hi>commerce,</hi> though not the <hi>Religious,</hi> of <hi>Opinion,</hi> and <hi>Worſhip,</hi> are unbroken by them, for the <hi>People</hi> not injured to make Warre upon them, for a <hi>feard, imaginary conſequence,</hi> or becauſe, being <hi>Atheiſts,</hi> 'tis poſſible that their example may ſpread, is an Act of <hi>Hoſtility</hi> which I confeſſe I am not able to defend.</p>
            <p>For thirdly, Sir, ſuch a <hi>Warre</hi> muſt either have for it's end, their <hi>puniſhment,</hi> or their <hi>Correction.</hi> Their <hi>puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> can be no true warrantable <hi>end,</hi> becauſe towards <hi>thoſe</hi> who ſhall thus make <hi>Warre</hi> upon them, they have not of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended. Nor can their <hi>Correction</hi> Legitimate ſuch a <hi>Warre.</hi> Becauſe all Correction, as well as Puniſhment, requires <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction</hi> in the <hi>Correctors,</hi> and <hi>Inflictors</hi> of the puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which one <hi>People</hi> cannot reaſonably be preſumed to have over <hi>another People independent,</hi> and no way ſubject to them. unleſſe we will allow, with that<note n="*" place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de jure belli &amp; pacis c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Author,</hi> that becauſe <hi>Naturall reaſon</hi> doth dictate that <hi>Atheiſme</hi> is pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhable, therefore they, who are not <hi>Atheiſts</hi> have a <hi>right</hi> to puniſh thoſe that are; which <hi>Coverruvias</hi> the Spaniard, who hath learnedly diſputed this poynt, and <hi>others,</hi> as learned as he, have not thought fit to grant.</p>
            <p>It hath been a <hi>Queſtion</hi> ask't, whether <hi>Idolatry</hi> be not a <hi>Crime</hi> of this <hi>puniſhable nature</hi> in one People by another, who are not guilty of that Crime. To which the beſt Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, which I have yet read upon that Subject doe anſwer <hi>negatively,</hi> that it is not. For though it be to be granted that among the ſeverall ſorts and kinds of <hi>Idolatry, One</hi> is more <hi>Ignoble</hi> and <hi>irrationall</hi> then <hi>Another;</hi> And ſo the offence towards <hi>God</hi> is greater or leſſe as the <hi>Objects,</hi> to which men
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:160373:15"/>terminate their <hi>Idolatry,</hi> are more <hi>vile,</hi> or <hi>honourable;</hi> As in thoſe old <hi>Heathens,</hi> 'twas a more faulty <hi>Idolatry</hi> to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip a <hi>Dogge</hi> or <hi>Crocodile,</hi> or <hi>Serpent,</hi> then to worſhip things of a <hi>Sublimer</hi> kinde, namely the <hi>Sunne,</hi> or <hi>heavenly bodies,</hi> or <hi>Soules</hi> of famous men departed; And though all ſuch <hi>Idolatries</hi> have deſervedly been thought to be ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny <hi>Affronts,</hi> and <hi>Robberies</hi> of the <hi>true God,</hi> whoſe worſhip is thereby miſplaced, and ſpent upon <hi>falſe,</hi> yet having left behind him in his whole <hi>Globe</hi> of <hi>Creation</hi> no exact <hi>figure</hi> or <hi>Character</hi> of Himſelfe, to be known or diſtinguiſht by, nor any plaine <hi>Teacher</hi> but his <hi>Scripture</hi> to informe men of <hi>vulgar understandings,</hi> that there is but <hi>one God,</hi> and that that <hi>one God</hi> is only an <hi>Intelligible spirit,</hi> and no part of this <hi>groſſe materiall World</hi> which we ſee, wherever the <hi>Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture</hi> hath not been heard of, if men (unable by the light of a <hi>Naturall diſcourſe</hi> to apprehend him as <hi>He</hi> is) have fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cied to themſelves a plurality of <hi>Falſe Gods,</hi> or made to themſelves falſe repreſentations of the <hi>true,</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17.30.</note> 
               <hi>God connived</hi> at it, as a piece of unaffected <hi>ignorance.</hi> which can never be a <hi>cauſe meritorious</hi> of a Warre to cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect it. Firſt, becauſe being only an Offence againſt <hi>God,</hi> and the <hi>Offendors</hi> being (as I ſaid before) <hi>free,</hi> and no way <hi>ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject</hi> to any People but themſelves, Any forraigne <hi>Nation</hi> (unleſſe they can ſhow the like Commiſſion from God to puniſh them, as the <hi>Jewes</hi> had to puniſh and root out the <hi>Canaanites</hi>) will want <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> and <hi>Authority</hi> to their Armes. Next, becauſe <hi>Idolatry,</hi> though it be a <hi>falſe Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> is yet as conſervant of <hi>Society</hi> (which diſtinguiſhes it very much from <hi>Atheiſme,</hi> and the deniall of Providence) as if 'twere <hi>true.</hi> Nor can I ſee why <hi>He</hi> who worſhips <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Gods,</hi> if he believe them to be <hi>Gods,</hi> ſhould leſſe feare puniſhment for his <hi>perjuries,</hi> or other <hi>Crimes,</hi> then <hi>He</hi> who only worſhips, and believes there is but <hi>one.</hi> Laſtly, becauſe though <hi>Idolatry</hi> be an <hi>Errour</hi> in men, yet being an <hi>Errour,</hi> without the light of <hi>Scripture</hi> to rectify it, hardly <hi>vincible</hi> in <hi>themſelves,</hi> and no way <hi>criminall</hi> towards <hi>others</hi> of a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:160373:15"/>more rectified <hi>Reaſon,</hi> 'Tis to be reformed by <hi>Argument,</hi> and <hi>perſwaſion,</hi> not <hi>violence,</hi> or <hi>force.</hi> Since a Warre made upon the <hi>Errours</hi> of mens <hi>mindes,</hi> is as unreaſonable, as a Warre made upon the <hi>Freedome</hi> of their <hi>Wills.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for this laſt reaſon, I conceive that the propagation of <hi>Chriſtian Religion,</hi> cannot be a <hi>juſt cauſe</hi> for a Warre upon thoſe who will refuſe to imbrace it. Firſt, becauſe ſuch a <hi>Refuſall</hi> may poſſibly ſpring from an <hi>Errour</hi> in the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, which even in a <hi>Preaching,</hi> and <hi>perſwaſive</hi> way would ſcarce be in the power of S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelfe, if he were on earth againe (unleſs he would joyne <hi>Miracles</hi> to his <hi>Sermons</hi>) to diſlodge. For though ſome parts of the <hi>New Law</hi> doe carry ſuch a <hi>Muſick</hi> and <hi>conſent</hi> to the <hi>Law</hi> of <hi>Nature,</hi> that they anſwer one another like two ſtrings wound up to the ſame tune; yet there be other parts, which though they doe not <hi>contradict</hi> it. are yet ſo <hi>unilluſtrable</hi> from the <hi>principles</hi> of <hi>Reaſon,</hi> that they cannot in a natur all way of <hi>Argumentation</hi> force <hi>aſſent.</hi> And you know, Sir, 'twould be unreaſonable to make <hi>Warre</hi> upon mens <hi>perſons</hi> for the reception of a <hi>Doctrine,</hi> which cannot convince their <hi>Minds.</hi> I muſt needs confeſſe to you, ſhould <hi>Chriſt</hi> now live in our daies, and Preach much harder <hi>Doctrines</hi> then thoſe in the <hi>Gospell,</hi> and ſhould confirme every <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> with a <hi>Miracle,</hi> as he did then, 'twould be an inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable peece of <hi>Infidelity</hi> in all thoſe who ſhould ſoe his <hi>Miracles</hi> not preſently to conſent, and yeeld beliefe to his <hi>Sermons.</hi> But ſomethings in his <hi>Doctrine</hi> appearing <hi>new</hi> and <hi>ſtrange</hi> to the World, and depending for the probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their <hi>Truth</hi> upon the <hi>Authority</hi> of his <hi>Miracles,</hi> And thoſe <hi>Miracles</hi> being <hi>Matters</hi> of <hi>Fact,</hi> wrought ſo many <hi>Ages</hi> ſince, and therefore not poſſibly able to repreſent themſelves to our <hi>times</hi> upon greater Authority and proofe, then the <hi>Faith,</hi> and generall <hi>Report</hi> of <hi>Tradition</hi> and <hi>ſtory;</hi> If any ſhall think they have reaſon not to believe ſuch a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port,</hi> they may alſo thinke they have no reaſon to believe ſuch <hi>Miracles,</hi> and by conſequence the <hi>Doctrine</hi> ſaid to be
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:160373:16"/>confirmed by them. In ſhort, Sir, the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> at that very time when the Preaching of it was accompanied with <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacles,</hi> obtained not alwaies that ſucceſſe which the <hi>ſaving Doctrine</hi> of it deſerved. The <hi>Jewes</hi> ſaies S. <hi>Paul</hi> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Require a ſigne;</hi> that is, they would believe it no far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then they ſaw <hi>Miracle</hi> for it; And the <hi>Greekes</hi> (That is, the <hi>learned Gentiles</hi>) <hi>ſeek after wiſdome;</hi> that is, They would believe no more of it then could be proved to them by <hi>Demonſtration.</hi> Nay, notwithſtanding all thoſe great Miracles which were wrought by <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> after him, S. <hi>Paul</hi> tels us at the 23. verſe of that Chapter, that the <hi>vileneſſe</hi> of Chriſts death did ſo diminiſh the <hi>Antho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity</hi> of his <hi>Doctrine,</hi> though confirmed by <hi>Miracles,</hi> that the Preaching of <hi>Him crucified,</hi> was a <hi>ſtumbling block to the Jewes,</hi> and <hi>Fooliſhneſſe to the Greekes.</hi> Next, Sir, As Chriſt hath no where commanded that men ſhould be <hi>compelled</hi> to receive the Goſpell by any <hi>Terrors</hi> or <hi>Inflictions</hi> of <hi>Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall puniſhments,</hi> ſo I finde that all ſuch endeavours are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unſutable to his <hi>practiſe.</hi> You know what his anſwer was to his two <hi>zealous Diſciples,</hi> who would have called for<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.54.</note> fire from heaven, to conſume thoſe <hi>Samaritans</hi> who would not receive him.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>v.</hi> 55, 56.</note> 
               <hi>ye know not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>of what ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit ye are of. The ſonne of man is not come to deſtroy mens lives but to ſave them.</hi> Which <hi>Anſwer</hi> of his was like the <hi>Commiſſion</hi> which he gave to his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> when he ſent them forth to Preach the <hi>Goſpell</hi> to ſeverall Citties. which extended no farther then this.<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 9.5.</note> 
               <hi>If they will not receive you, ſhake off the duſt of your feet againſt them, for a Teſtimony</hi> that you have been there. Agreeable to this practiſe of Chriſt is that <hi>Canon</hi> which paſt in the <hi>Councell</hi> of<note n="*" place="margin">C. de Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciis diſt. <hi>45.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Toledo,</hi> which ſaies, <hi>pracipit ſancta Synodus Nemini deinceps ad cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendum vim inferre, 'Tis ordered by this holy Syned, that no man be henceforth compelled to believe the Goſpell.</hi> A <hi>Canon,</hi> which I wiſh the men of the <hi>Countrey</hi> where 'twas made had worne in their <hi>Enſignes</hi> when they made Warre upon the <hi>Indians.</hi> And agreeable to this Canon, is the ſaying of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:160373:16"/>
               <hi>Tertullian, Lex nova non ſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ultore gladio; The new Law allowes not it's Apoſtles to revenge the contempt of it by the Sword.</hi> And agreeable to this ſaying of <hi>Tertullian</hi> is that paſſage in<note n="*" place="margin">In Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nâ Hiſtoriâ.</note> 
               <hi>Procopius;</hi> where one tells <hi>Juſtinian</hi> the <hi>Emperour,</hi> that in ſtriving to <hi>force</hi> the <hi>Samaritans</hi> to be Chriſtians by the Sword, he made himſelfe <hi>ſucceſſor</hi> to the two <hi>over zealous Apostles,</hi> who, becauſe they would not receive their <hi>Maſter,</hi> would have deſtroy'd them by <hi>fire.</hi> This then being ſo, to deale freely, Sir, both with <hi>you</hi> and your <hi>Friend,</hi> as often as I read the writings of ſome of our <hi>hot Reformers,</hi> who think all others <hi>Infidells</hi> who are not of their <hi>Opinions,</hi> And whoſe uſuall language 'tis towards all thoſe who differ from them in <hi>Poynts,</hi> though in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves <hi>indifferent,</hi> and no way neceſſary to Salvation,<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke</hi> 14.28.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, make <hi>Covenants,</hi> raiſe <hi>Armies,</hi> ſtrip them of their <hi>Eſtates,</hi> and <hi>compell them to come in,</hi> me thinks a peece of the <hi>Alcoran</hi> is before mee; and the <hi>Preachers</hi> of ſuch <hi>unchriſtian Doctrines,</hi> though they walke our <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh ſtreets</hi> in the ſhape of <hi>Aſſembly, Proteſtant Divines,</hi> ſeem to me to be a <hi>Conſtantinople Colledge</hi> of <hi>Mahomets Prieſts.</hi> To ſpeak yet more plainly to you, Sir, I am ſo farre from thinking it a peece of <hi>Chriſtian Doctrine,</hi> to Preach that 'tis <hi>lawfull</hi> (if it may not be done by <hi>perſwaſion</hi>) to take from men the Liberty, even of their <hi>erring Conſcience,</hi> that the <hi>new Army</hi> which ſhall be raiſed (which I hope never to ſee) for the proſecution and advancement of ſuch an <hi>End,</hi> however they may be <hi>Scots</hi> or <hi>Engliſh-men</hi> by their <hi>Birth,</hi> will ſeem to me an <hi>Army</hi> of <hi>Muſſell-men:</hi> and to come into the field with <hi>Scymitars</hi> by their ſides, and <hi>Tuli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pants,</hi> and <hi>Turbants</hi> on their Heads.</p>
            <p>How farre <hi>Defenſive Armes</hi> may be taken up for <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> cannot well be reſolved without a <hi>Diſtinction.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Sir, that if ſuch a warre fall out between Two <hi>Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Nations,</hi> That which makes the <hi>Aſſaylants</hi> to be in the <hi>wrong</hi> will neceſſarily make the <hi>Defendants</hi> to be in the <hi>Right,</hi> which is (as I have proved to you) a want of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:160373:17"/>
               <hi>rightfull power</hi> to plant <hi>Religion</hi> by the <hi>Sword.</hi> For in all ſuch <hi>Reſiſtances,</hi> not only <hi>They</hi> who fight to preſerve a <hi>true,</hi> but <hi>They</hi> who fight becauſe they would not be compelled to part with a <hi>falſe Religion,</hi> which they beleeve to be a <hi>true,</hi> are <hi>innocent</hi> alike. The Reaſon is, (which I have inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mated to you before) becauſe All <hi>Religion,</hi> being built up. on <hi>Faith,</hi> and <hi>Faith</hi> being only <hi>Opinion</hi> built upon <hi>Autori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> and <hi>Opinion</hi> built upon <hi>Autority,</hi> having ſo much of the <hi>Liberty</hi> of mens <hi>wills</hi> in it, that they may chuſe how farre they will, or will not beleeve that <hi>Autority,</hi> No man hath <hi>Right</hi> to take the <hi>Liberty</hi> of another mans <hi>will</hi> from him, or to preſcribe to him what he ſhall, or ſhall not <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve,</hi> though in all <hi>outward things</hi> that <hi>other</hi> have ſold his <hi>Liberty</hi> to him, and made his <hi>Will</hi> his <hi>Subject.</hi> where both parties, therefore, are <hi>Independent,</hi> and <hi>One</hi> no way <hi>Subiect</hi> to the <hi>Other, Religion</hi> it ſelfe, though for the propagation of <hi>it ſelfe,</hi> cannot warrant the <hi>One</hi> to invade the Others <hi>Freedome.</hi> But 'tis permitted to the <hi>Invaded,</hi> by both the Lawes of <hi>God,</hi> that of <hi>Nature,</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> too, (unleſſe they be guilty of ſome preceedent <hi>Injury,</hi> which is to be repayred by <hi>Satisfaction,</hi> not ſeconded by <hi>Reſiſtance</hi>) to repell <hi>Force</hi> with <hi>Force.</hi> And if the <hi>Army</hi> now in Conduct under Sir <hi>Thomas Fairefax</hi> be of this perſwaſion thus <hi>ſtated,</hi> I ſhall not think it any <hi>ſlander</hi> from the Mouth of a <hi>Presbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian,</hi> who thinks otherwiſe, to be called an <hi>Judependent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If a <hi>Prince</hi> who is confeſſedly a <hi>Prince,</hi> and hath <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme power,</hi> make Warre upon his <hi>Subjects</hi> for the <hi>propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation</hi> of <hi>Religion,</hi> the Nature of the <hi>Defence</hi> is much alter'd. For though ſucha <hi>Warre</hi> (whether made for the Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a <hi>falſe Religion</hi> or a <hi>true</hi>) be as <hi>uniuſt</hi> as if 'twere made upon a <hi>forreigne Nation,</hi> yet this injuſtice in the <hi>Prince</hi> cannot warrant the taking up of Armes againſt Him, in the <hi>Subject.</hi> Becauſe being the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> or <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme</hi> within his own <hi>Kingdome,</hi> As all <hi>power</hi> concerning the publick, ſecular <hi>Government</hi> of it reſolveait ſelfe into <hi>Him,</hi> ſo doth the ordering of the <hi>Outward</hi> exerciſe of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:160373:17"/>too. In both Caſes he is the <hi>Judge</hi> of <hi>Controverſies.</hi> Not ſo <hi>unerring</hi> or <hi>Infallible,</hi> as that all his <hi>Determinations</hi> muſt be received for Oracles, or that his <hi>Subjects</hi> are ſo obliged to be of his <hi>Religion,</hi> that if the Prince be an <hi>Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> a <hi>Mahumetan,</hi> or <hi>Papiſt,</hi> 'twould be diſobedience in them not to be ſo too. But let his <hi>Religion</hi> be what it will; let him be a <hi>Ieroboam,</hi> or one of ſuch an <hi>unreaſonable Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try,</hi> as to command his people to worſhip <hi>Calves,</hi> and Burn Incenſe to Gods ſcarce fit to be made the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> Though he be not to be obeyed, yet he is not to be <hi>reſiſted.</hi> Since ſuch a <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> would not only change the Relation of <hi>inequality,</hi> and <hi>Diſtance</hi> between the <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> and ſo deſtroy the <hi>Supremacy</hi> here given him by S. <hi>Peter,</hi> but 'twould actually enter <hi>duell</hi> with the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>God;</hi> which ceaſeth not to be ſacred as often as 'tis wickedly imployed. <hi>Irreſistibility</hi> being a <hi>Ray</hi> and <hi>Beame</hi> of the <hi>Divine Image,</hi> which reſides in the <hi>Function,</hi> not in the <hi>Religion</hi> of the <hi>Prince.</hi> Who may for his <hi>Perſon,</hi> perhaps, be a <hi>Caligula,</hi> or <hi>Nere,</hi> yet in his <hi>Office</hi> ſtill remaine Gods <hi>Deputy</hi> and <hi>Vicegerent.</hi> And therefore to be obeyed, even in his <hi>unjuſt commands,</hi> though not <hi>actively</hi> by our compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, yet <hi>paſſively</hi> by our ſufferings. This <hi>Doctrins</hi> as 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to the Scripture, and the practice of the <hi>pureſt,</hi> and moſt <hi>primitive</hi> times of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſo I finde it illuſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the famous <hi>example</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian Souldier,</hi> and the cenſure of a <hi>Father</hi> upon the paſlage. This <hi>Souldier</hi> being bid to burne <hi>Inconſe</hi> to an <hi>Idoll,</hi> rcfuſed; But yeelded him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be caſt into the <hi>fire.</hi> Had he, when his <hi>Emperour</hi> bid him worſhip an <hi>Idoll,</hi> mutinied, or turn'd his <hi>speare</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him (ſaies that Father) he bad broken the <hi>fift Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement</hi> in defence of the <hi>ſecond.</hi> But ſubmitting his Body to be burnt, (the only thing in him, which could be <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled</hi>) in ſtead of committing <hi>Idolatry</hi> he became himſelfe a <hi>Sacrifice.</hi> I could, Sir, ſecond this with many other Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples, but they would all tend to this one pious, <hi>Christian Reſult,</hi> that <hi>Martyrdome</hi> is to be preſetred before <hi>Rebellion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:160373:18"/>
Here then, if I ſhould ſuppoſe your <hi>Presbyterian Friends</hi> charge to be true, (a very heavy one I confeſle) that the <hi>King miſcounſelled</hi> by a <hi>Prelaticall Court Faction,</hi> when he firſt Marcht into the field againſt the <hi>Armies</hi> raiſed by the two Houſes of Parliament had an intent to ſubvert the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and to plant the Religion of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in it's ſtead, yet unleſſe he can prove to me, that from that time he actually ceaſt to be <hi>King,</hi> or the two Houſes to be his <hi>Subjects,</hi> or (notwithſtanding their two Oathes of <hi>Supremacy</hi> and <hi>Alleageance</hi>) that in ſo doing he forfeited his <hi>Crowne,</hi> and was no longer <hi>over all perſons, and in all Cauſes as well Civill as Eccleſiaſticall within the circuit of his three Kingdomes ſupreame Head and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,</hi> I know no Armes which could lawfully be uſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Him; but thoſe which S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> uſed againſt an <hi>Arian Emperour, Lachrymas &amp; Suſpiri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, Sighes</hi> &amp; <hi>Tears,</hi> and <hi>Prayers</hi> to <hi>God</hi> to turne his heart. And therefore, Sir, when your <hi>Friond</hi> doth next aske you, How it could ſtand with the ſafe <hi>conſcience</hi> of any <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant,</hi> to ſtand an idle ſpectator, whilſt <hi>Queen Marus</hi> daies were ſo rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to break in upon him, that He was almoſt reduced to this hard <hi>choyce,</hi> either to follow the <hi>Times</hi> in the <hi>new</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected faſhion of Religion, or live in danger of the <hi>ſtake,</hi> and <hi>Faggot,</hi> if he perſiſted in the <hi>old,</hi> you may pleaſe to let him know from <hi>me,</hi> That as I have no <hi>unruly Thirſt,</hi> or <hi>ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regular Ambition</hi> in me to dye a <hi>Martyr,</hi> Nor am ſo much a <hi>Circumcelleo,</hi> as to <hi>court,</hi> or <hi>wooe,</hi> or (in caſe it fled from me) <hi>enthuſiaſtically</hi> to <hi>call</hi> upon me my own <hi>Death</hi> and <hi>Execution;</hi> So, if it had been my <hi>Let</hi> to live in the <hi>fiery times</hi> He ſpeaks of, when a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> was put to death for an <hi>Heretick,</hi> as I ſhould not have quarreld with the <hi>Pawer</hi> that condemned me, ſo I ſhould have kiſt my <hi>funerall pile;</hi> And ſhould have thought it a high peece of <hi>Gods</hi> favour to me, to call me to <hi>Heaven</hi> by a way ſo like that of his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell</hi> in the Book of<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>c.</hi> 13.20.</note> 
               <hi>Judges,</hi> who aſcended thither in the <hi>Flame,</hi> and <hi>aire,</hi> and <hi>perſume</hi> of a <hi>Sacrifies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:160373:18"/>
But what if this be only a <hi>Jealouſie</hi> and <hi>ſuspition</hi> in your <hi>Friend?</hi> Nay what if it have been the <hi>Diſguiſe,</hi> and <hi>paint</hi> to ſome <hi>Ambitious mens</hi> deſignes, who, to walke the more ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curely to their <hi>darke</hi> and <hi>politick ends,</hi> have ſtiled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the <hi>Defendours,</hi> when they have all this while been the <hi>Invadors;</hi> And have called the King the <hi>ſubverter,</hi> who hath all this while (to his power) been the <hi>Defender</hi> of this <hi>Religion?</hi> This certainly if it be proved, will very much Inflame and aggravate their <hi>ſinne,</hi> and dye it in a deep <hi>ſcarlet,</hi> through all the progreſſe of it. But becauſe I rather deſire to caſt a <hi>mantle</hi> over their <hi>ſtrange proceedings,</hi> then to adde to their <hi>Nakedneſſe,</hi> which hath at length <hi>diſcover'd</hi> it ſelfe to all the World, all that I ſhall ſay, to deliver ſo much <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> from ſo much <hi>miſrepreſentation</hi> is this. That the <hi>report,</hi> (which at firſt <hi>poyſon'd</hi> the mindes of ſo many <hi>Thouſand</hi> well minded <hi>people</hi>) That the <hi>King</hi> had an intent, by this warre, to deſtroy the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> could at moſt have no other <hi>parent</hi> but <hi>ſome</hi> mens either <hi>crafty Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice,</hi> or <hi>needleſſe Feare,</hi> appears clearly in this, that after all their great <hi>Diſcoveries,</hi> they have not yet inſtanced in one conſiderable <hi>Ground</hi> fit to build more then a <hi>vulgar Jealou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy</hi> upon. The <hi>Kings affection</hi> to the <hi>Queene,</hi> His <hi>Alliance</hi> and <hi>confederacy</hi> with <hi>Popiſh Princes</hi> abroad, and the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of his Raigne towards his <hi>Popiſh Subjects</hi> at home, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>premiſes</hi> as unfit to build this Inference and concluſion upon, that, <hi>Therefore</hi> He took up Armes that he might in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce their Religion, as his in <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> were; who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it <hi>lightued</hi> when <hi>Socrates</hi> took the Ayre, thought that his <hi>walking</hi> cauſed that <hi>commotion</hi> in the <hi>skyes.</hi> For that the Root and Spring of ſuch a <hi>report,</hi> could be nothing but their own <hi>deluded fancy,</hi> they muſt at length confeſſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe with their <hi>Faith</hi> they have caſt off their <hi>Charity</hi> too. Let your Friend, Sir, read over any one of His Majeſties <hi>Declarations,</hi> and what <hi>ſacred Thing</hi> is there by which he hath not freely and uncompelled, obliged and bound Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to <hi>live,</hi> and <hi>dye</hi> a <hi>Proteſtant?</hi> By what one <hi>Act</hi> have
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:160373:19"/>theſe many <hi>Vowes</hi> been broken? Who made that <hi>Court Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,</hi> which would have <hi>miſcounſelled</hi> him to bring in <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery?</hi> Or let your <hi>Friend</hi> if he can, name, who thoſe <hi>Miterd Prelates</hi> were, who lodged a <hi>Papiſt</hi> under their <hi>Rotchet.</hi> If he cannot, let him forbeare to hold an Opinion of his <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Clergy,</hi> which <hi>Time</hi> (the <hi>mother</hi> of <hi>Truth</hi>) hath ſo <hi>demonſtratively</hi> confuted; And let him no longer ſuffer himſelfe to be <hi>ſeduced</hi> by the <hi>malitious writings</hi> of <hi>thoſe,</hi> who, for ſo many years, and from ſo many <hi>Pulpits</hi> have breathed Rebellion, and Slander with ſuch an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled <hi>Boldneſſe</hi> and <hi>Sting,</hi> that I cannot compare them to any thing ſo fitly as to the <hi>Locusts</hi> in the<note n="*" place="margin">Revel, <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Revelation,</hi> which crept forth of the <hi>Bottomleſſe pit;</hi> every one of which wore the <hi>Crowne</hi> of a <hi>King,</hi> and had the <hi>Tayle</hi> of a <hi>Scorpion.</hi> In ſhort, Sir, If he have not ſo deeply drunke of the <hi>Inchanted cuppe,</hi> as to forget himſelfe to be a <hi>Subject,</hi> let him no longer endanger himſelfe to taſt of their Ruine too, who, for ſo many years, have dealt with the beſt <hi>King</hi> that this <hi>Nation</hi> ever had, as <hi>Witches</hi> are ſaid to deale with <hi>thoſe</hi> whom they would by <hi>peece meale</hi> deſtroy, firſt <hi>ſhap't</hi> to themſelves his <hi>Image</hi> in waxe, then <hi>pricks,</hi> and <hi>ſtab'd</hi> it with needles, ſtriving by their many Reproaches of his <hi>Government,</hi> and Defamations of the <hi>Biſhops,</hi> to reduce his <hi>Honour</hi> by degrees to a <hi>conſumption,</hi> and to make it <hi>Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh,</hi> and <hi>pine,</hi> and <hi>wither</hi> away in the <hi>Hatred,</hi> and <hi>Diſaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi> of his <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, perhaps Sir, your <hi>Friend,</hi> and <hi>I,</hi> are not well agreed upon our <hi>Termes:</hi> If therefore he doe once more ſtrive to perſwade you, that (notwithſtanding all this which I have ſaid to the contrary) the <hi>King</hi> would, if he had not been hindered, have deſtroyed the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> pray de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire him to let me know what he mean by the <hi>Religion</hi> which he calls <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> Doth he mean that Religion which ſucceeded <hi>Popery</hi> at the Reformation, and hath ever ſince diſtinguiſht us from the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome?</hi> Doth he meane that Religion which ſo many <hi>Holy Martyrs</hi> ſeal'd
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:160373:19"/>with their <hi>Blood,</hi> that for which Queene <hi>Mary</hi> is ſo <hi>odious</hi> and Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> ſo <hi>pretious</hi> to our memories? Laſtly. Doth he meane that Religion which is compriſed in the 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> and confeſt to be Proteſtant by an <hi>Act</hi> of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament?</hi> If theſe be the <hi>Markes,</hi> theſe the <hi>Characters</hi> of it, let him tell me whether <hi>this</hi> be not the <hi>Religion</hi> which the King in one of his<note n="*" place="margin">Cabinet Opened.</note> 
               <hi>Letters</hi> to the <hi>Queene</hi> calls the <hi>only Thing of difference between Him and Her,</hi> that's deareſt to Him. whether this alſo, be not the <hi>Religion,</hi> in which, if there be yet any of the <hi>old Ore,</hi> and <hi>Droſſe,</hi> from whence 'twas extracted, Any thing either <hi>eſſentially,</hi> or <hi>accidental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly evill,</hi> which requires yet more <hi>ſifting,</hi> or a more <hi>through Reformation.</hi> Any thing of <hi>Doctrine</hi> to offend the <hi>ſtrong,</hi> or of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> or <hi>Ceremony,</hi> to offend the <hi>wenke,</hi> His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty have not long ſince offered to have it paſſe the fiery <hi>Try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all</hi> and <hi>Disputes</hi> of a <hi>Synod legally called.</hi> To all which que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, 'till <hi>He</hi> and his <hi>Com presbyters,</hi> give a ſatiſfying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, however they may think to hide themſelves under their old <hi>Tortoiſe-ſhell,</hi> and cry out, <hi>Templum Domini,</hi> the <hi>Temple of the Lord,</hi> They muſt not take it ill if I aske them one queſtion more, and deſire them to tell me, whether this be not the Religion which they long ſince compelled to take <hi>flight</hi> with the <hi>King,</hi> and which hath ſcarce been to be <hi>found</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome,</hi> ever ſince the time it was depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of the <hi>Sanctuary</hi> it had taken under the <hi>Kings Stand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then, being ſo, hath your <hi>Friend,</hi> or his <hi>fellow Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblers,</hi> yet a <hi>purer,</hi> or more <hi>primitive Notion</hi> of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion,</hi> which compared with the Religion which we and our Fathers have been of, will prove it to be <hi>Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous,</hi> and no better then a <hi>hundred years ſuperſtition?</hi> Let them in <hi>Charity</hi> (as they are bound not to let us periſh in our <hi>Ignorance</hi>) ſhew us their <hi>Modell.</hi> If it be more agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to the <hi>Scripture</hi> then <hi>Ours,</hi> have more of the <hi>white Robe,</hi> and not of the <hi>new invention;</hi> we may, perhaps, be their
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:160373:20"/>
               <hi>Converts;</hi> And their <hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> meeting with out <hi>Peace</hi> may mutually <hi>Kiſſe each other.</hi> In the mean time, Sir, I hope they will not define the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ſo by <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatives,</hi> as to make it conſiſt wholly in <hi>No Biſhops, No Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy,</hi> or <hi>No Common-Prayer Booke.</hi> Theſe <hi>we,</hi> (not yet convinced to the contrary) doe hold to be good <hi>Conſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives,</hi> but not <hi>Eſſentialls,</hi> of that which we call the <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toſtant Religion</hi> of our <hi>Side;</hi> Their <hi>Negation</hi> then, can be no <hi>true Eſſentiall Conſtituent</hi> of the ſame Religion on theirs.</p>
            <p>There is but One <hi>poſitive Notion</hi> more in all the world, under which I can poſſibly underſtand <hi>Them,</hi> when They ſay, They have all this while Fought for the <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion;</hi> That is, that by the <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> (if they meane <hi>any Thing,</hi> or if this have not bin the <hi>Diſguiſe</hi> to a more <hi>dangerous ſecret</hi>) They meane the <hi>Defence</hi> of their <hi>New Directory,</hi> and their at length concluded <hi>Government</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Presbyters.</hi> If this be their Meaning, (And truely if I ſhould rack my <hi>Invention,</hi> I cannot make it find another) The <hi>Second part</hi> of that moſt <hi>Holy,</hi> and <hi>Glorious Cauſe,</hi> which hath drawne the eyes of <hi>Europe</hi> upon it, and renderd the <hi>Name</hi> of a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant,</hi> a <hi>Proverbe</hi> to expreſſe <hi>Diſloyalty</hi> by, That <hi>Pure, Chaſt, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>irgin,</hi> without <hi>ſpott</hi> or <hi>wrinkle-Cauſe,</hi> which like the <hi>Scythian Diana</hi> hath been fed with ſo many <hi>Humane Sacrifices,</hi> And to which, as to another <hi>Moloch,</hi> ſo many <hi>Men</hi> as well as <hi>Children,</hi> have been <hi>compell'd</hi> to paſſe through the <hi>Fire,</hi> reſolves it ſelfe into this <hi>Vnchriſtian Bloudy conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> That an <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of profeſt <hi>Proteſtant Divines,</hi> have <hi>adviſed</hi> the <hi>Two Parliaments</hi> of <hi>England</hi> and <hi>Scotland,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt <hi>Subjects,</hi> to take up Armes againſt the <hi>King,</hi> their <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Soveraigne,</hi> Have thereby ſet <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> in a <hi>Flame,</hi> been the <hi>Authors</hi> of more <hi>Proteſtants ſlaine</hi> in a <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill,</hi> then would have ſerved to recover the <hi>Palatinate</hi> by a <hi>Forraigne Warre,</hi> for nothing but this <hi>vnneceſſary novell, accidentall Conſideration,</hi> That the <hi>King</hi> (vnleſſe <hi>compell'd</hi>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:160373:20"/>by <hi>Forces</hi>) would never conſent (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> indeed without <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury</hi> could) to the <hi>Change</hi> of an <hi>Ancient, Primitive, Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolike, Vniverſally received Government</hi> of this <hi>Church</hi> by <hi>Biſhops,</hi> for a <hi>new, vpſtart, Muſhrome, Calviniſticall Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> by a <hi>Motley Presbytery,</hi> of <hi>Spirituall</hi> &amp; <hi>Lay-Elders.</hi> Which being (As I have hither to by <hi>Principles</hi> taken both from <hi>Reaſon,</hi> and <hi>Scripture</hi> proved to you) in the moſt <hi>fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable</hi> ſenſe, a <hi>Reſiſtance,</hi> if not an <hi>Jnvaſion</hi> of the <hi>Higher Power,</hi> &amp; that Higher Power being<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Gods Ordinance</hi> muſt needs be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. or a <hi>Warre</hi> made againſt <hi>God Himſelfe.</hi> And the <hi>Authors</hi> of it (unleſle they <hi>repent,</hi> and betake themſelves to a timely <hi>returne</hi> to their <hi>Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence</hi>) in danger to draw upon themſelves this other, <hi>ſad, tragicall irreſiſtible Concluſion,</hi> which S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">V. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> tels us is the inevitable <hi>Cataſtrophe</hi> of <hi>Diſobedience,</hi> which is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, you may Engliſh it, <hi>ſwift Deſtruction.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, Sir (Though all <hi>weake Defences</hi> have ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Nature of <hi>prevarication</hi> in them, and <hi>he</hi> may in part be thought to <hi>betray</hi> a Cauſe, who <hi>feebly</hi> argues for it) I have return'd you a <hi>large Anſwere</hi> to the <hi>two Quere's</hi> in your <hi>ſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Letter,</hi> which if you ſhall you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to call <hi>Satiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction</hi> you will very much aſſiſt my <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which will not ſuffer me to thinke that <hi>I,</hi> in this <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> have ſaid <hi>more</hi> then <hi>Others.</hi> Only being ſo fairely invited by <hi>you</hi> to ſay <hi>ſomething,</hi> to have remain'd <hi>ſilent,</hi> had been to have <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt</hi> my ſelfe <hi>convinced;</hi> And my <hi>Negligence,</hi> in a <hi>Time</hi> ſo <hi>ſeaſonable</hi> to ſpeak <hi>Truth</hi> in, might perhaps, in the <hi>Opinion</hi> of the <hi>Gentleman,</hi> your <hi>Friend,</hi> have ſeemed to take part with <hi>thoſe</hi> of <hi>his ſide,</hi> againſt whoſe <hi>Cauſe,</hi> though not their <hi>Perſons,</hi> I have thus freely <hi>armed</hi> my <hi>Pen.</hi> Sir I ſhould think my ſelfe <hi>fortunate,</hi> if Any Thinge which I have ſaid in this <hi>Letter</hi> might make him a <hi>Proſelyte.</hi> But this being rather my <hi>wiſh</hi> then my <hi>Hope,</hi> all the <hi>Succeſſe</hi> which this <hi>Paper</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpires to is this, that you will accept it as a <hi>Creature</hi> borne at your <hi>Command;</hi> And that you will place it among your other <hi>Records,</hi> as a <hi>Teſtimony</hi> how much greater my <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires,</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:160373:21"/>then my <hi>Abilities</hi> are to deſerve the <hi>ſtile</hi> of being thought worthy to be</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From my Chamber <date>
                     <hi>June</hi> 7. 1647.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Your affectionate ſervant <hi>JASPER MAYNE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
